<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the conscience A discourse wherein is playnely declared, the vnspeakeable ioye, and comfort of a good conscience, and the intollerable griefe and discomfort of an euill conscience. Made by Iohn Woolton, minister of the Gospell. Anno. 1576.</title>
            <author>Woolton, John, 1535?-1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842036</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842036</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 719:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the conscience A discourse wherein is playnely declared, the vnspeakeable ioye, and comfort of a good conscience, and the intollerable griefe and discomfort of an euill conscience. Made by Iohn Woolton, minister of the Gospell. Anno. 1576.</title>
                  <author>Woolton, John, 1535?-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by H. Iackson, for Humfery Toye,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1576]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-N⁴ O² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6659:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6659:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>OF THE <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A DISCOVRSE <hi>wherein is playnely declared,</hi>
               </hi> the vnſpeakeable ioye, and comfort of a good Conſcience, and the intollerable griefe and diſcomfort of an euill Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MADE BY IOHN Woolton, Miniſter of the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO.</hi> 1576.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted by H. Iackson, for Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery Toye.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6659:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>TO THE RIGHT worſhipfull, Sir Iohn Jylbert, knight, Iohn Woolton wiſheth proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe in all worldly affaires: and in the life to come, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall felicity.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONG MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine leſſons, which <hi>Seneca</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Lucilius,</hi> touching the leadyng of an honeſt and godlye lyfe: he borroweth one of the Epicure, in mine opinion not to be accounted the meaneſt, which he would haue his friende to imprint diligently and deepely in the bottome of his breſt. <hi>Let vs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Senecca lib. 10. epiſt. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſo lyue</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>as if the eyes of all men were bent toward vs: let vs ſo ſtudie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe with our ſelues when we are alone, as if ſtraungers did viewe our ſecret cogitations.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cur actions and deeds alwayes vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> 
               <hi>Manye faultes and miſchiefes ſhalt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd: if thou imagine that thou haſt a witnes of thy doings alway at thy elbowe.</hi> Which leſſon euery chriſtian ought to learne, not
<pb facs="tcp:6659:3"/> imagining (as <hi>Seneca</hi> would haue vs) that <hi>Cato Lelius,</hi> or ſome ſuch graue man; dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alwayes with open eyes looke vppon vs: but perſwading our ſolues as the truth is in deede, that we haue with vs alwayes preſent, waking &amp; watching vs, a ſage and graue Cenſor of lyfe &amp; maners (our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in ſteede of a thouſande witneſſes.</note> I ſay) which according to the como<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> proue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be is in ſteede of a thouſand witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, This conſcience ſo wonderfully frami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and faſhioned in man by ahnighty God, to be a witneſſe &amp; an informer of mankinde <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is a ſcoolemeſter vuto him.</note> and of the law of Nature, which comman deth things that be honeſt, &amp; forbiddeth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> contrary. Sommone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> vs as it were before the tribunall feate of God, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time accuſing, ſometime excuſing, nowe puniſhing and now abſoluing vs; for God did of his good will and vpright iuſtice or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne this watchman in our Nature, that ioy ſhould follow lawdable and honeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and contrariwiſe Sorrow, abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and deſperate deedes: that anguiſhe and dolour might be a continuall torme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of vngodlineſſe, and a deſtroyer of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious natures. There can nothing happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">The ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence.</note> to a mortail man more gréeuous, heaup, or miſerable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a guilty Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which all
<pb facs="tcp:6659:3"/> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are delighted with the filthineſſe of ſin, are compelled to carry about with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a booke of notes wherein they write all <note place="margin">Chriſoſt in pſal. 50.</note> their offences. Wherof <hi>Bernhard</hi> ſpeaketh after this manner. <hi>An euill Conſcience is a witneſſe of our debtes, a Iudge, a tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bernhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe accuſeth vs, ſhe iudgeth vs, ſhe puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs, and ſhe condemneth vs, which if it lie hid for a time yet it breaketh out at the laſt, eſpecially at the hower of death, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ende of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agaynſt their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> 
               <hi>a thouſande euidences againſte men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Whereof <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, <hi>Henrie</hi> king of Fraunce, <hi>Iames Latomus of Louayne,</hi> and dyuers others, are euident &amp; knowne examples, who felt theſe fearefull angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes <note place="margin">Pantalion chron. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Iho. Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius et alii.</note> of the Conſcience, and the ſence of Gods wrath for theire wilfull obſtinacie, and cruell tirrany againſt Chriſt and hys church, and at their departure out of this worlde; with dolefull voyces, and fearefull ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>clamacions vttered in their griefe, to ſuch as had acceſſe vnto them.</p>
            <p>The good conſcience on the other ſide as it were a braſen wall, againſt vntrue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes, <note place="margin">Herat. lib. 1. epiſt.</note> perill and daungers, and maketh the gool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, when they are perſecuted, beaten and tyed in yron chaynes, voyde of dolor and payne: and when they come before the
<pb facs="tcp:6659:4"/> mightie men of this worlde, they ſhrinke not, they faynte not, they waxe not pale, neyther chaunge their countenance. <hi>Paule</hi> being a priſoner and brought before <hi>Felix:</hi> was not abaſhed hymſelfe, but with hys aunſweres, which were full of diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and might, he made the gouernour to tremble and quake: which cannot be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to any thing, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſincere good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of his wherof himſelf ſpeaketh thus. <note place="margin">Act. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Herein I endeuored my ſelfe to haue alway a cleare Conſcience toward God, and toward men.</hi> Let vs then beware that we wounde not our Conſcience, and whether we be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone at home, or in company abroad, let vs accoumpt that the principall witnes. For as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth: <hi>Euery man hath of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ambroſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in epiſt ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> 
               <hi>his own minde &amp; Conſcience a ſeuere iudge, either puniſhing the guilty, or acquiting the guiltles and innocent:</hi> And <hi>Sencca</hi> writeth to <hi>Lucillius</hi> diuinely after this manner. <hi>To what end doe we hide our ſelues, and decline the eyes, &amp; eares of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: A good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the company vnto hym, but an euel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Seneca epiſt. 96.</note> 
               <hi>is in doubt and feare, euen, when we are alone. If thoſe thinges that we doe be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, what need we to care if the whole world looke vpon vs: but if they be vnhoneſte, wee</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6659:4"/> 
               <hi>muſt needes knowe them our ſelues, O miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable men that we are, if we contemne this witneſſe.</hi> Seing then that ſo great ioye and comfort iſſueth out of a good conſcience, &amp; ſo great heuines and diſcomfort co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from an euell Conſcience, I haue thought good to write ſomewhat briefly and ſhortly, as wel of the one as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other. Neither was it my purpoſe to proſecute all things, that belong vnto this matter (which to doe would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more leiſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I yet haue, &amp; a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger worck then this treatiſe) and who ſo liſt to reade more hereof, I referre him to Saynt <hi>Bernhard, Melancthon, Hemingius,</hi> and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to <hi>Ioh. Riuius,</hi> who wil plentifully ſatiſfie the greedy Reader, deſirous to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand more of this matter: but I haue collected out of all theſe, ſo much as ſéemed vnto me moſt conuenient and neceſſary for the Chriſtian reader in this behalf. Which if I haue not accompliſhed ſo pithely and eloquently as perhaps ſome of our Engliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hiloſophers or Retoricians would haue done, I wil not contend in rendring a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my doings: but do giue them leaue to amend that which is amiſſe, for as <hi>Cinicall</hi> taracion is deteſtable, ſo is charitable ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduerſion in my iudgement cc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:5"/> not miſdoubting but that the godly reader will rather accept hereof with like affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it is deliuered: then diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain my want of ability to offer it ſo per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tc in all poynts, eyther as the matter deſerueth, or I my ſelfe deſired.</p>
            <p>Theſe my Laboures (ſuch as they be) I offer vnto your worſhip, as a taken of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny good will, and obſeruancy toward the ſame, for your great loue and intire affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward me: which you haue diuers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day ways, in benefites be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>owed vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and mine, effectually declared. And bicauſe I certaynly know that in your life &amp; dayly actions, you doe not any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing willingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the teſtiniony of a good Conſcience, which you only ground vpon Gods word, the ſureſt foundation in all your building, and cleareſt lighte and lanterne to directe your paths to euerlaſting life. This treaty of the ſame matter cannot be vnmeete to be preſented vnto you: which your whorſhip according to your good nature, will I truſt accept in good part: the liuing God bleſſeand preſerue you, and that verteous Land your wife, long in al proſperity. From Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceter the 20. of Mirche.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips humbly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>und. Iohn Woolton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6659:5"/>
            <head>¶ OF THE CONSCIENCE, a Treatiſe collected by Iohn Woolten.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE ARE TWO principall partes of mans <note place="margin">After what forte there are two partes of manners Souls.</note> Soule (as I haue plainely declared in my Treatiſe of of the immortalitie thereof) which of neceſſitie muſte con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> in all exerutions and actions of vertue. For although the naturs of the Soule be ſimple and without compoſition and deuiſion, yet they vſe to attribute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him certaine partes: to witte according to hys ſundry and dyuers operations. As for example take, we acknowledge in the fyre two powers or qualities: the one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming or heating, the other ſhewing or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering from darkeneſſe all thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: euen ſo when men ſpeake of the partes of the <hi>Soule,</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urpe that name for the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and effectes of the ſame. Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> partes are called <hi>Reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and Wyll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſheweth what is ſeemely and <note place="margin">Reaſon. Will.</note> conue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ent to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or to be leſt vndone: and the ſeconde eyther coueteth and purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith as good, that which was propoſed by
<pb facs="tcp:6659:6"/> reaſon, eyther elſe declineth and auoydeth the ſame as euell. Hereof came that apte and fine ſentence. <hi>All mortal actions, are as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> were ingendred and conceiue by Reaſon, but are broughte foorth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by Wyll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as brute beaſtes haue no ſparke of reaſon, (whereby man both diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th moſt far from them, and reſembleth very neere an expreſſe Image of the diuine nature) ſo haue they no <hi>Will</hi> but <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Appetite,</hi> and with the one, they are le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de to their <note place="margin">Brute be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ner Wyll but ſenſe &amp; Appetite.</note> naturall foode, with the other they di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne thinges holſome, from hurtfull. Some there are, that terme this Appetite in beute beaſtes <hi>Will</hi> without <hi>Reaſon;</hi> for that domine creatures bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of minde, and vidnerſtanding, are ledde toward thinges with a certain ſecrete motion, and in ſtinct of nature, rather ſhen with any free will, choyſe, or vnderſtanding. For they in ſhee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Reaſon, haue giuen vnto them by Gods a certaine naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kill, to defend and to ſerue them ſelues. This Will or Appetite which perſeweth thinges, conceiued by Sence, is common to man with beaſtes: euen as the Sences, as well externall as
<pb facs="tcp:6659:6"/> internall, (from whence this Appetite yſſeweth) is unparted equally to man and beaſt ſauing to the ſence of all bruſe beaſts commonly is more quick and perſite, then that which is in man, and in beaſtes this fence is the ſupreme and moſt excellent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie. In man it is but a ſeruaunte, or handmayde to Intelligence, or vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>And Reaſon was geuen vnto man, not <note place="margin">The effecte of Reaſon.</note> onely to fearche after vertue, that the <hi>Will</hi> ſhould embrace the ſame, but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oderate carnall motions, and to bridle their rage, and furnes, Albeit <hi>Reaſon</hi> very often, as it were ſhadowed and ouerralle with darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, iudgeth peruerſly and corruptly: and not that alone, but alſo is ſo infirme and weake, that it cannot reſtrayne euill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined any thinge, Will is either ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerth <note place="margin">The off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, or elſe ſo weake, that ſhe doeth not excute the ſame. Whereof may ryſe no ſmall queſtion, ſeeing that the very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of will is vertue her ſelfe, ſhewed and opened vnto her by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> howe it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e that we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ed headlong,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:7"/> as it were violently to miſchiefe, ſo that pernitious and deuiliſhe affections, doe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerrule that excelent faculty guien by God to couet that which is good &amp; honeſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Apoſtle himſelfe complayneth. <hi>That good thing which I woulde doe, that I doe not: and that euill which I would not, that I doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Medea</hi> burning in madde loue with <hi>Iaſon:</hi> hauing wraſtled with hir ſelf much and long, yet coulde ſhe not ouercome that furor with Reaſon, for thus ſhee talketh with hir ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Video meliora probo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, deteriora ſequor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the ſcripture reſolueth this doubt, and telleth vs that through the fall of our <note place="margin">why will is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſobydi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Reaſon</note> firſt parentes, and by originall ſinne deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending into all mankind from that route: theſe diſeaſes of the minde, theſe ſwarmes of perturbations, and theſe continuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictes betwene reaſon and luſte doe budde out and ſpring. Therfore great néede haue we to craue Gods ayde &amp; helpe: by whoſe grace we maye vanquiſhe and ouercome that rebellion of deſires and affections: for without that neyther Reaſon nor. Will is of power eyther to doe good, or elſe to reſiſt
<pb facs="tcp:6659:7"/> the crooked and frowarde mocions of man.</p>
            <p>In the chiefe and principall parte of the <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſience in reſpect of Indgement is placed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the minde but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections &amp; motions it is in the hart.</note> Soule which we call Reaſon, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly place the Conſcience, that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workmanſhip of God, being according to the prouerbe in ſteede of a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, not onely commaunding things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and diſwading the contrary, but more ouer aſciting vs as it were before the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall ſeate of the diuine Maieſtie, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time accuſing and ſometing excuſing. In <note place="margin">The opeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Conſcience</note> this matter puniſhing and another acquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Whereof as I minde to write ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what at this time: ſo will I not follow the ſubtyle and thornye maner of the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who with great curioſitie of definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deuiſions, haue altogether darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned rather then lightened this matter: but ſo farre forth as my abiliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will extende, doe purpoſe with breuitie and perſpicute, to proſecute this matter. Wherevnto if I cannot reach, according to my earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, yet I truſt at the leaſt hereby to moue ſome happy witte to poliſh this enterpriſe, for it were greate pitty that comfortable Conſcience ſhould be any longer mute and domme as a ſtraunger: but that ſhée might
<pb facs="tcp:6659:8"/> franckly and freely ſpeake vnto our conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men in our Engliſh tongue.</p>
            <p>And that I maye keepe ſome certayne <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>odot this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ca and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ruf.</note> niethode in the tranſlation hereof, which they call <hi>Analyſis</hi> ſeemeth moſt concienient for me to follow. Firſt I will put downe the definition, comprehending and infol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it were in one bundell, the whole matter generally. Then I will open and reſolue into partes, euerye porciorr of the ſame. In the which <hi>Analyſis,</hi> beſides fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry and diuers things, a man may eaſely ſee the principles and groundes of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, howe ſhe is placed in the minde: hir force and power in examining all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall actions. This done I will ſpeake of the difference betwene a ſounde, and a corrupt Conſcience, and of the effects of them both: to wyt, of the ſolace &amp; comfort of the one in aducrſitie, and of the priuie woundes of the other euen in worldly felicitie. Laſtly, I will diſcourſe certaine queſtions incicent to this matter: which being finiſhed, I truſt that the knowledge of Conſcience, which hath bene ſecret and obſcure, ſhall ſhewe hir ſelfe ſomewhat plainely to the eyes, and ſhall ſtirre vp in men a maruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb facs="tcp:6659:8"/> loue and deſire of a ſineere conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in that golden and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Epiſtle to the Romaines ſpeaketh of the Gentils in this wiſe. <hi>For when the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">a to ſcrip expreſſing Conſcience</note> 
               <hi>Gentils which haue no lawe, doe by nature the things conteyned in the lawe, they hauing not the lawe, are a lawe vnto themſelues.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Which ſhewe the effect of the lawe, written in their hartes, their conſcience alſo bearing witneſſe, and their thoughtes accuſing one another or excuſing.</hi> In this ſentence of ſaint Pauſe I obſerue foure thinges, firſte he ſayth that the worck of the law is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their hartes: this worck of the lawe, is the diſcelning betweene thinges honeſt, and vnhoneſt: Secondly he ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhew it. For in mainteyning of Religion, they acknowledge that there is a God to be worſhipped: and in that they puniſh crimes and heynous offences, they profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues defendors of honeſty, and Iuſtice. Thirdly he maketh metion of the inward teſtimony of the conſcience. Fourthly he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>howeth what manner of Teſtes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is euen by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uident Arguments ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing or exeuſing, out of the which this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitio is deduced. The Conſcience <hi>is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:6659:9"/> naturall intelligence of the law, ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Conſcience.</note> 
               <hi>in the minde or power vnderſtanding, whereby we allow good actions and diſalow euill actions.</hi> Which iudgement planted in the internall man by God, breedeth in the execution of vertue, a quietneſſe and reſte of minde, and in vice a wonderfull verati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, puniſhing and afflicting the <note place="margin">Thre thigs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued.</note> man guilty: but there are thrée, thinges in the minde, which are to be obſerued for the better vnderſtanding of this matter.</p>
            <p>The firſte is the vnderſtanding whiche <note place="margin">Ondirſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emplatyre.</note> they call contemplaty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, buſied alwayes in the ſtudy and ſearching out of thinges, and this is that better part of the minde which alway (as the Philoſophers ſaye) aſpireth to the beſte. In this they place <hi>Syn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which is the kéeper and conſeruer of noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <note place="margin">Ariſto. li. 1. ethick.</note> or vnderſtandinges, which are bredde with vs by nature, examining what is, and what is not expedient. And therefore it is fayde that ſhe miniſtreth propoſitions to reaſons and argumentes, which are called <hi>Sillogiſmes practical,</hi> Such propiſition are theſe that follow, honeſt thinges are to bee done, vnhoneſt thinges are not to be done: Out of which two groundes or principles
<pb facs="tcp:6659:9"/> infinite ſinguler propoſitions are deriued, ſeruing in arguments, or as I called them <note place="margin">Sinteriſis eſt habitus innatus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruans principia moralia et practica ſicut Sine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia ſpecu labilia.</note> 
               <hi>Sillogiſmes practicall.</hi> And it is ſo called for that it examineth and inquireth a reaſon out of the law of nature, of the quality of all humaine accions.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place of the minde is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence practicall, which conſiſteth in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And therin is the Conſcience proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly placed, for that of the difference of Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhe putteth down and as it were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the leſſe propoſition or aſſumtion in the Sillogiſme or Argument in this wiſe, <hi>Sinteriſis</hi> or <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> miniſereth this propoſition in <hi>Hector. Honeſt thinges are to be done.</hi> Then Conſcience apprehendeth this aſſumtion. <hi>To defend a mans countrie and to die therefore is honeſt.</hi> Agayne <hi>Sinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſis</hi> or <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> deliuereth this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in <hi>Oedipus. Fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy and detoſtable deedes are to be eſchewed.</hi> Then the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence aſſumeth. <hi>But Inceſte with my mother and paricide, are moſte deteſtable deedes.</hi> And ſo vnderſtanding and Conſcience rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth in all other accions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly in the minde there is Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Iudgement or decerm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> pronouncing of all accions, whether
<pb facs="tcp:6659:10"/> they be worthy of prayſe or diſprayſe. And as ſhe ſerued in generality in the Maior or firſt propoſition, ſo as a witty Iudge, ſhee deſcendeth vnto the ſpecial caſe in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion and geueth ſentence. For examples ſake, <hi>Intelligence contemplat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue</hi> in Hector, deliuereth this propoſition. <hi>Honeſt deedes are praiſe worthy.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Conſcience ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth: <hi>To defend my countrie and to dye in defence of it, is an honeſt dede,</hi> laſtly iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment geueth ſentence, <hi>Therfore to defend</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Examples plainely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing this matter.</note> 
               <hi>my country, and to die in defence of it, is prayſe worthy.</hi> Agayne Intelligence deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth this propoſition to <hi>Oedipus. Moſte vile and filthy actes deſerue moſte greucuſe puniſhmentes.</hi> Conſcience addeth: <hi>Inceſte with my Mother and paricide, are moſt vile and filthy actes.</hi> Finally Iudgement geueth ſentence: <hi>Therefore inceſte with my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and paricide, deſerue moſt greeuous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes.</hi> The former argument bredde in <hi>Hectors</hi> breſt vnſpeakeable courage, in ſo much that he vtterly contemned death. For <hi>Polidamas,</hi> did aduiſe him not to goe out among the Erecians that day: becauſe the fliyng of Birdes did portend ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy euent. <hi>Hector</hi> aunſwered ſtoutely,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:10"/> whether the byrdes flye on the right hande towarde the Eaſt, or on the left hande to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Weſte, I am reſolued to obey great <hi>Iupiter</hi> his counſayle: meaning that valyant mocion of his minde to be <hi>Iupiters</hi> counſayle, whereby he was excyted to doe uoble and valyant deedes. Neyther coulde ſuperſticious obſeruacion of tymes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde him from doing his duetie, eſpecially in the common perill of his naturall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye. Contrariwiſe the latter <hi>Sillogiſme</hi> kyndled ſuch tormenting &amp; burning fyres, that through impaciencie &amp; inwarde griefe for wickedneſſe by him committed, he rent out his owne eyes. <hi>Oedipus</hi> verily was a <note place="margin">Oedipus.</note> Noble fellowe and king of the <hi>Thebanes,</hi> who albeit he contenmed <hi>Tireſias</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, caſting in his teethe inceſtious mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end he was ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted with one teſtimonie of his owne conſcience, that he confeſſed himſelfe guyltie and a caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, not worthie to beholde any longer the light of Heauen, and euen ſo <hi>Iocaſta</hi> hys mother with an halter ſtrangled hir ſelfe.</p>
            <p>There are infinite ſuch examples of <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſmes,</hi> or argumentes practicall in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture. <hi>Ezechias</hi> knoweth that there
<pb facs="tcp:6659:11"/> is but one true God, whoe onely is to be called vpon and worſhipped, which thing <hi>Syntereſis</hi> or <hi>Intelligence</hi> telleth him out of the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement: Then Conſcience <note place="margin">The ground of Ezechias his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>net.</note> aduoucheth the ſame: &amp; laſt of all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concludeth in this maner. <hi>The true &amp; lyuing God, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the God of Iſraell is only to be worſhiped: But Idolatrie maintayneth manye Gods, euen in deſpite of the lyuing God, therefore Idolatrie is to be aboliſhed, Ezechias</hi> armed wyth thys iudgement of Conſcience, cutteth downe the Groues, taketh downe the braſen Serpent, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth Idols, and aboliſheth Idolatry, and committeth the euent to God. And ſayth: <hi>For theſe are no Gods but woode and ſtone, euen the worke of mens hande.</hi> And in lyke maner <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtayeth his hande from <note place="margin">Dauid. 1. Sa. 24.</note> ſlaying of <hi>Saule,</hi> euen offered vnto hym in the Caue, bicauſe he knoweth that he is Gods annoynted, and a magiſtrate by his ordinance, reaſoning thus with himſelfe. <hi>No violence is to bee vſed towarde Gods magiſtrate: But Saule is Gods magiſtrate, therfore I muſt doe him no violence.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples alſo are worthy conſideration, as <hi>Regulus</hi> led eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wtth ciuill honeſty kéepeth
<pb facs="tcp:6659:11"/> promiſe made vnto his enimy, reaſoning thus with himſelfe: <hi>There is nothing more ſeemely for a noble hart, then to conſider the end of his accions, and his owne honeſty: But to keepe my oath made vnto my ennemie is the end of my accions, and apperteineth to my honeſtie, therefore I will keepe my oth made vnto my ennemie, euen in the perrill of my life.</hi> Such like examples are in delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, counſayles and examples in all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of the actes and deedes of mortall men.</p>
            <p>I am not ignoraunt that ſome handle this matter otherwiſe, deuiding <hi>Reaſon</hi> into <note place="margin">Riuiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 1. de conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: &amp; hauſit ex Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</note> two partes. The Superiour and the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioure <hi>Reaſon.</hi> And that would haue that light of mans minde preſcribing thinges deuine and eternall, to be the higher Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and that which is buſied about tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and profitable thinges to be the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour. Moreouer ſome there be alſo that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Conſcience, putteth downe the Minor propoſition, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion. And touching the diuiſion of Reaſon, they vſe <note place="margin">Riuius lib. de conſc. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentit ab</note> ſuch examples as follow. Imagin <hi>Caeſar</hi> deliberating with himſelfe, whether hée ſhoulde take Armoure agaynſte his natiue
<pb facs="tcp:6659:12"/> country. Conſcience aunſwereth that hée <note place="margin">omnibus aijt enim conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmo practico.</note> ought not to doe it. <hi>Reaſon Superiour</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth it, becauſe it is contrary to Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to the law of nature, being in it ſelfe vile and vnhoneſt: <hi>Reaſon Inferioure,</hi> alloweth the ſame becauſe it is in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> world a thing infantous and reprochful, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall very perillous. Out of theſe <hi>Sinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſis</hi> or Iudgement inferreth: that it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable &amp; by no meanes to be attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In lyke maner miagine <hi>Popilius</hi> dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berating with himſelfe whether he might execute <hi>Antonies</hi> commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndement &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Cicero.</hi> Conſcience telleth that he ought not to murder <hi>Cicero</hi> by any meanes. <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Superior</hi> ſayth, that he ſhall be noted of great ingratitude, if he murder that man who ſometime defended him in a matter of lyfe and death, &amp; procured his delyuerance. <hi>Reaſon Inferior</hi> addeth that he ſhal procure common hatred &amp; mallice of all good men, if he murder a man that hath moſt notably preſerued the liberty of his country, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Sintereſis</hi> or Iudgement gathereth, that Ingratitude as a moſt odious &amp; deteſtable thing is to be auoyded. And thus you ſée all the partes of a <hi>Sillogiſme</hi> which they call
<pb facs="tcp:6659:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>practick:</hi> wherin reaſon probable examine morall actions by the law of Nature &amp; by principles deryued out of the ſame. I call Principles thoſe Notices or knowledge which are planted &amp; graued in our minds by good ſentences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon &amp; knowne vnto al men, wherevnto we without gaineſaying. doe wyllingly and naturally aſſent. Such are theſe. <hi>Thankes are to be yeelded to thoſe which deſerue them. Euerie man ought to haue his owne. Wee ought to imitate no man.</hi> And theſe principles which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne to our duetie and vocation in a cyuill lyfe are named <hi>practicke,</hi> &amp; their naturall habite <hi>Sinteriſis.</hi> But thoſe <hi>Theorick</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which properly belong to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation &amp; knowledge, they terme the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of principles, as for example. <hi>The whole is greater then a part. Of nothing can nothing be made,</hi> &amp; ſuch lyke. I thought it requiſite to interlace this ſhort admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the termes or wordes, which wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in theſe caſes vſe: whereof many cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious queſtions are of many moued, which may be the better diſcerned, theſe things knowne for my part, I thinke the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion to be moſt commodious and playne
<pb facs="tcp:6659:13"/> for knowledge and vnderſtanding ſake, otherwiſe moſt certayne it is that theſe thinges differ not in mans minde, if you reſpect their ſubſtance and eſſence: being in déede mingled &amp; confuſed one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: onely for inſtruction ſake, they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate in thought and cogination. For the heauenly Philoſopher S. Paule nameth the whole <hi>Sillogiſme,</hi> whereof I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before, mans conſcience.</p>
            <p>It is euidence by the premiſſes that the <note place="margin">Cauſes why diuers men be of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences.</note> quality of Conſcience varieth, according to the condition of mens factes. For in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare and loue GOD, there is a good Conſcience, whiche procéedeth of vertues and ſincere deliberations, and déedes brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vnto man an incredible ioye &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thinges well done: And an euell Conſcience, in wicked and euell perſons which by reaſon of vile and abhomiuable facts, of ſhame and diſcredite receiued, doth fret &amp; knaw the minde with great vntolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable greefes and fraunces.</p>
            <p>Wherein it is to be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, that Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence taketh not theſe differences of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Iudicatiue which is a naturall gifte, &amp; therefore to be nombred among good things
<pb facs="tcp:6659:13"/> and is ſometime named the lighte of the minde, ſometime the naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> time the inſtruction of <hi>Reaſon:</hi> But the <note place="margin">The things which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience chife in reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</note> Conſcience taketh ſuch qualities of theſe thrée thinges: Of the facte paſte, of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent affection of the hart, and of the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. For if the minde be throughly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his Innocency, it reioyceth, and cheriſheth good hope, and is called a good Conſcience the difynition whereof is as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>A good Conſcience is a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioyfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce <note place="margin">Defynyty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> of our former life, well paſte and ſpente, hauing a ſure hope and expectation of ſome happy euent: Or thus, a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is a gladſome motion of the harte conioyned with a perfite knowledge of a fact well done, where it is called not Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence but Conſcience. Which good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is aſwell the cauſe of chearefulneſſe in the face and countinaunce, being but an outward token of the inward affection: as alſo the breder and conſeruer of the ſolace and ioye in the minde conceaued of good factes and happy euents. For better decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hereof I will examine certayne ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes particulerly.
<pb facs="tcp:6659:14"/> And for examples ſake let vs looke vppon theſe rich men of the world, hauing at their own will abundantly thinges neceſſary to a ſwéete and pleaſaunt life, and therefore are generally almoſte reputed bleſſed and happy. If a man with more inſight examin their eſtate, he ſhall not finde any men ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more miſerable, or more trembling &amp; fearing Gods wrath and vengeaunce, then they if at any time they happen to call an accompt of them ſelues, by what meanes they haue heaped theſe thinges together. I doe not nowe ſpeake of ſuch as haue gotten riches and increaſed their ſubſtance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mans iniurie, if any ſuch be (for in déede ſuch byrdes are rarely ſéene:) But I note thoſe that wythout reſpect of right or wrong, doe onely or chiefely ſéeke for gaine, neglecting in the meane ſeaſon thoſe things which principally doe adorne and bewtifie man. Whiles ſuch men doe recorde their couen and frawde in gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring gayne: what agonies and paſſions of minde? what gna wings and woundes of Conſcience doe they abide? wherwith they bring as it were ſcourged and whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, doe ſuſteyne inwardly vnſpeakeable miſery
<pb facs="tcp:6659:14"/> in their externall ſhewe of felicitie. On the other ſide they that with honeſt and lawful meane growe to be ritche, and haue vſed no celluſion nor hurtful guile in their trade of lyfe, muſt néedes inwardly reioyce, and giue endeleſſe praiſe and thankes to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie for his goodneſſe mercie towarde them. Moreouer, thoſe meli that excell in <note place="margin">Of bewty and ſtrength</note> bewtie, ſtrength, health, or other giftes of the body, muſt néedes be ſayde to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receyued great benfites of God, but thoſe that abuſe their bewtie to vnchaſte loue, their ſtrength to hurt their neighbor, their health to filthie and vnlawfull pleaſures, what miſeries and ſorrowes ſhall they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde <note place="margin">Of Nobility</note> ſuſteyne. We maye iudge the fame of Nobilitie, of power, of glorie, of honor and ſuch lyke. For if onely vertuo be the true and perfite Nobilitie (as the Poet ſayeth:) Then ſurely they may not rightly be called Noble, that onely deſcend of a famous houſe, and haue gotten Armes and Nobilitie by their renowmed Aunceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that is with other mens vertues: or elſe (as often it happeneth) by our notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pyraries, robbres, or murders: but thoſe onely that with their owne worthye
<pb facs="tcp:6659:15"/> and excellent deeds haue aduaunced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or being ſprong of Noble paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by imitation, doe withall their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, ſtudy to reſemble them from whence they came Such the as are Noble in déede, doe conceiue of their excellent and worthy déedes towarde their countrie an vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioy in their Conſcience: whereas the Noble vnnoble with his guyltie conſcience (howſoeuer men fawne vpon him or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him) is inwardly vexed &amp; tormented.</p>
            <p>And whereas that is a right power and <note place="margin">The abuſe of power &amp; auttoryty.</note> good deminion, to haue many whoſe welth and proſperity a man may tender and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whoſe liberties &amp; lawes a man maye defende and conſerue: they that doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, muſt néedes haue déepe griefes, and perillous woundes in their mindes. The example of auncient Tyrauntes in all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories verifie the ſame: as <hi>Dioniſius, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris, Nero,</hi> and manye moe innumerable. Whoſe great and manyfolde miſeries that I may omitte, which haue vered them day and night, by meanes of their monſtrous déedes, yet I note this one thing very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy obſeruation, that ſuch excellent &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy wightes as haue deſerued the loue of
<pb facs="tcp:6659:15"/> all men: theſe Tyrauntes haue not onely alwayes feared and hated: but alſo haue vaniſhed or expelled out of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes, yea and ſometime haue put them to drath, and the ſtowte &amp; valyant men they hate, leſt they ſhould attempt with force to brydle their crueltie: the wiſe men: leaſt they ſhould moderate their raſhneſſe and impotencie: the tuſt men, leſt the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſhoulde be ledde away through admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their vertues. Well ſayd <hi>Saluſt, Kings &amp; Tyrants doe alwayes more ſuſpect good men then badde, and other mens ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are terrible vnto them.</hi> Remouing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from them ſuch men, whoſe vertues their naughtie mindes deteſt and abhorre, they conioyne with Cutthrctes and Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynes, and commit bothe themſelues and their ſubiectes to their Regimentes, And yet hereby can they not exclude feare, for they alwayes miſtruſt their garde and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kéepers of their bodye, and thinke that the edge of the ſworde is alwayes euen at their necks. <hi>Dioniſius</hi> doing is often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, who hangyng a ſharpe poynted ſworde by the heire of a horſetaile ouer his friends heade: playnely paynteth out the
<pb facs="tcp:6659:16"/> inwarde conſcience and outwarde lyfe of Tyrantes.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Denys</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> writeth ſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the company and ſocietie of men: and ledde his lyfe with Fugitiues, Ruffyans, and Barbarous people, and reputed al ſuch for his enimies, in whome there appeared any ſhewe of vertue and honeſtie. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe thoſe Princes that ſéeke to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the welth of their ſubiects, that yéelde vnto them lawfull and néedefull liberties: that thinke with themſelues the proper du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and part of a Prince, not to conſiſt in precious garments, nor delicious banquets and vayne pleaſures, not in great heapes of Gold and Siluer: But in pietic, vertue, and prudencie: Such Princes I ſaye will not haue neyther of their counſayle, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Court, ryotous Bankeruptes and Ruffyans, but will be aſſiſted with ſuch who bend all their ſtudies for the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie of their countrie: and will content himſelfe onely wyth the friendſhyp and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie of good men.</p>
            <p>True glorie is much accounted of, and <note place="margin">True glory</note> not without cauſe. It is a <hi>Renowmed fame for ſome notable and excellent deede done:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6659:16"/> 
               <hi>hauing annexed vnto it the loue and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of good men.</hi> But I praye you what pleaſure can thoſe conceyue hereof, who being altogether voide of vertue &amp; honeſty, haue eyther by ſome miſchicfe gotten them fame amongſt the multitude: eyther by Uſerie, Extorcion &amp; oppreſſion of the poore, are become notable? aſſuredly ſuch men do heare their owne conſcience tell them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tale: and in continuance of tyme that vayne perſwaſion lyke ſmoke vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye. Contrariwiſe, theſe that by their owne domerits are magnified and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to true honor and glorie by good men: muſt néeds enioy vnſpeakable ſolaces and pleaſures in their myndes: and do account the ſame a ſufficient rewarde for all their trauayles and aduentures.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Pompeius Magnus,</hi> When the people did ſalute hym, calling hym <hi>the father of their countrie,</hi> acknowledged that he had receyued that daye a moſt ample &amp; worthy reward for all thoſe laboures which hée had ſuſteyned for his country. Therfore welth, Riches, Powre, Glory, Honour, ſtrength, helth, and ſuch like, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the madd mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude meaſureth mannes felicity cannot
<pb facs="tcp:6659:17"/> bring vnto man any ſtable or firm comfort vnleſſe they haue anexed vnto them the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of a ſincere Conſcience, for that pleaſure is not durable, which ariſeth of in continency, of ambition, of auarice, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancy, and of others of that Rable.</p>
            <p>All theſe certeynlye are deceiue able and ſpotted repaſtes. Moſte truely is it ſayde, <hi>The feare of the Lorde delighteth the harte, and giueth ioy and gladneſſe continualy. But the vngodly haue no ioy at all.</hi> Thus they that leade a godly and honeſt life, albeit they contemne or haue not theſe ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectations, and doe not follow <hi>Venus</hi> court neither haunt delicate fare, nor eſtéeme dauncing, wanton playing, and other va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, yet no doubte they liue in greater myrth, and ioye then thoſe carnall men: Who what with the furors of theyr Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the remembraunce of Gods wrath and malediction hanging ouer theyr head, and the continuall feare of the greate daye of doome, doe leade a wretched and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life.</p>
            <p>Aduerſity and miſery ſo gréeuous to this our nature is it not mitigated and made more eaſy by reaſon of a good Conſcience:
<pb facs="tcp:6659:17"/> That ſaying is no more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon then true. <hi>It is the greateſt ſolace to wante Guylt.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne: <hi>It is no finale thing to be innocent in aduerſitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And euen ſo it fareth in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, wherein if happily at anye tyme there happen ouerthwart euentes to mens good conſultations or when good actions are ſiniſterly interpreted by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ll men: what other conſplation doth ſo effectuallye diminiſh griefes &amp; ſorrowes of the minde, as an vpright Conſcience. Which thing you maye euidently ſée by reading the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne hyſtories in <hi>Furnis Camillus, Scipio. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icanus</hi> and many others, who ſalued the déede woundes of exyle and baniſhment, and the ingratitude of their Citizens, with the certaine knowledge and remembrance of their valyaunt actes in defence of their Countrie! <hi>Socrates</hi> vmuſtlye condemned, ſpake ſo deuinely (as <hi>Cicero</hi> recordeth) eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when he ſhoulde ſuppe vp the deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: that he ſéemed not to deſcend into hell, but to aſcende into heauen. <hi>Aepamino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>das</hi> ſtriken into the breſt with an arrowe figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in defence of his countrie, &amp; throughe faintneſſe inforced to lye downe in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilion,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:18"/> woulde not ſuffer the arrowe to be plucked out, before he might knowe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of the battayle: And at laſt when ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges was brought him of the flight and conqueſt ouer his enimies, he then at the laſt wylled the arrowe to be drawne out: and pouring out his heart bloude, he dye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> myldely, gratulating ſo happy ſucceſſe vn his countrie: The holy ſcripture propoſeth vnto vs ſtore of ſuch examples: and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Iob</hi> preſſed with ſo great calamity; and almoſt ſwallowed vp with miſeries: when his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were gone: his wife raging and rayling, and his friends in ſtéede of honye, gaue vnto hym talke as bitter as Gaull, what lenitiue had he but a good conſcience, borne vp with a ſtrong fayth, whereby hée cried ſaying. <hi>Though he kill me, yet will I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 19.</note> 
               <hi>truſt in him ſtill;</hi> and albeit his frendes tould him that he was forſaken of God, yet he held faſte by the Ancker of Gods prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that my redeemer liueth, and that I ſhall riſe agayne at the laſt day, and ſhalbe compaſſed agayn wiſh my ſkinne, and ſhall ſee god in my fleſh. Ioſeph</hi> that Godly and chaſte young man, being chayned in
<pb facs="tcp:6659:18"/> ſhe ſtockes, what ſolace had hee in the déepe dungeon, but his ſincere mind and vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Conſcience: And euen ſo it was with <hi>Eliazarus,</hi> with <hi>Paule,</hi> and with all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in their diſtreſſe, for <hi>Eliazarus ſayth O lord I am piteouſly tormented in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but I willingly ſuffer all theſe thinges for thy names ſake, Paule</hi> being certified by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabus,</hi> of the afflictions which he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at <hi>Ieruſalem. I (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he) am ready not only to be bound, but alſo to ſuffer death for the name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> The Apoſtles like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being ſcorged for preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Went away with Ioy, that they were found worthy to beare infamy for the name of the Lord Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The principal cauſe of theſe thinges was doubtleſſe a good conſcience, which writeth ſorrowe into ioy, calamity to felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to conclude, death into lyfe it ſelfe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6659:19"/>
               <head>OF THE EVELL AND COR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Conſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S THERE IS IN</hi> GOD that ſupreme and nigh maieſt is of God, a wiſedome deſcerning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene good &amp; euil things: and alſo a will wiſhing goodneſſe, with a deuine delectation &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: &amp; contrariwiſe nylling that which is naught, and with great indignation and anger reiecting and puniſhing the ſame. Euen ſo hath he created the lyfe of man: that there ſhoulde be certaine lawes as it were notices or admonitions of the mind, commaunding thinges honeſt, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the contrary, beſides theſe he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed magiſtrats that they ſhould defend the good, and puniſhe the euill. And to this ende were thinges thus ordered and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the creation: that men might learne that there is both a God, being a wiſe and iuſt Iudge: and there withall that manne ſhould knowe and perceyde himſelfe to be the ymage of God: whome he ought to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate and followe. For God is neyther knowne of heauen nor of earth: of plants:
<pb facs="tcp:6659:19"/> neyther yet of beaſtes, although they obey him in theire kinde, but Aungelles and men onely hath he ſo created, that he might he obeyed, knowne &amp; worſhipped of them, and that they being faſhioned lyke vnto God: might not pyne away and dye wyth impietie and vexation of minde: but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their hartes agréeable to right reaſon and iudgement, might reioyce in good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as well before as after the facte.</p>
               <p>But in this corrupt and wounded na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, mans hart burneth as it were wyth flames, méere contrary to right iudgement and at the firſt trembleth not to runne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to miſchiefe. Nowe for that it concerneth Gods iuſtice to puniſhe and route out ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and rebellious natures: therefore hath he conioyned the dolor and anguiſhe of the Conſcience, following wicked and miſcheuous deedes, that might (as it were an hangman) puniſhe and execute offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And although this ſorrowe he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what dull nowe and then in perſons, yet at the laſt, God doth ſo kindle it in the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that they tremble and quake, and are oppreſſed (as it were) with the noyſe of the thunder as it is ſayde in the Pſalme. <hi>In
<pb facs="tcp:6659:20"/> thy anger thou ſhalt vexe and trouble them.</hi> Whereof <hi>Plato</hi> wryteth excellently in this <note place="margin">Plato pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub.</note> wiſe. <hi>When an euill man draweth towarde his ende, he is ſodainely ſtriken with a foure and care of ſuch thinges, as he once thought not of before: and thoſe talke of Deuils of Hell and of paynes which the wicked ſuffer there where of he made a ſcoffe and ſtale ieſt, doe then miſerablye encoumber his minde, wherby he faleth into an examination of his former life. And recording his vile and filthy actes: hee is quyet neyther waking not ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: &amp; often times he ſturteth in his ſleepe, as it were a fearefull childe out of his dreame, and ſo lyuing awhyle, he droupeth away, in euill hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophocles</hi> wryteth, that <hi>Oedipus</hi> beyng olde and blynde, was ledde to <hi>Athens</hi> by <note place="margin">Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Oedipus.</note> his daughter <hi>Antigona.</hi> Who dying there, was buried in the Temple of <hi>Erinnyus.</hi> By the which fable he ſignifieth the vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et Conſcience at the hower of death of all ſuch as haue ledde an vnhoneſt lyfe. For <note place="margin">Erinnius.</note> 
                  <hi>Erinnyus</hi> by interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are nothing elſe then contentious perturbations of the minde, by reaſon of an euill Conſcience, which alwayes wayte vpon vnhoneſt actes
<pb facs="tcp:6659:20"/> and déeds. And they are ſayd to be minde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill, for that condigne puniſhment, for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actes are neuer forgotten, whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be for a time prolonged, yet this is the very property and effect of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riunius</hi> that when miſchiefe and payne is leaſt looked for, then it falleth moſte grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly. Thus much I thought: good to note touching the occaſions of doloures, and gréefe in the euell conſcience, now lette vs conſider the difinition of the ſame.</p>
               <p>An euell Conſcience is a heauy and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The difini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> motion of the hart, conioyned with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowlege of a deteſtable fact. For aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly furies doe alwayes purſue and chaſe the wicked, not with burning torches and fire brandes, as inter Iudes and playes ſette out, but with hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res of Conſcience, and anguiſh of minde, wayting alwayes vpon miſchieuous men, euen as the ſhade we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the body, not ſuffering them to beeath and as it were to pauſe one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuente from trembling and feare. And for this cauſe onely <hi>Seneca</hi> commendeth that ſaying of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pienre: <hi>The gilty man may happily hide himſelfe ſometime, but he hath no aſſured confidence to eſcape.</hi> Whiche
<pb facs="tcp:6659:21"/> thinges as they are true, ſo are they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with Hiſtories through<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute all tymes and ages. <hi>Tacitus</hi> reporteth that <hi>Tiberius</hi> vex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with ſuch torment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto the Senat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in this wiſe: <hi>What ſhould: I write vnto you my Lordes, or how ſhould I write, or rather what ſhoulde. I not wryte, I at this inſtant All the Gods of heauen at ons rather diſtroy the then to pine awaye dayly thus as I doe.</hi> Such plagues and tormentes had <hi>Tiberi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> inwardly, by his monſtrous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dings; Neyther is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the purpoſe <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which a certayne man vt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered. <hi>If the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of Titaunts minds might be vnlocked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſi ſho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſee their mangled wound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, for as it fareth with the body by reaſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtripes, and blowes, euen ſo it the minde at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oil reſite and torne with cruelty, filthy luſt, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>udo malice,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tiberius.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſuch like.</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tiberius</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o wante of any<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worldly thinges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that might ſerue to ſolace and comford <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> afflicted mind, yet was he hot able by any of meanes to eaſe or conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate the tormentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and paynes of his Conſcience. <hi>Suetonitis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Caligula.</note> wryteth of <hi>Caligula,</hi> who ſeemed neyther to care for God nor man, yet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt roum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and glauneing of thundering and
<pb facs="tcp:6659:21"/> lightning, he would winke and couer hys face: &amp; when with greater terror heauen and earth ſeemed both to ſhake, &amp; to burne with f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, he woulde runne into corners and hyde himſelfe. The ſame Author alſo noteth home <hi>Nero,</hi> after he had murdered <note place="margin">Nero.</note> his naturall mother, was ſo greeuouſlye ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in conſcience, that he could not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, neyther with ioyfull ſhow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es and acclamations of the people, nor with the gratulacions of the <hi>Senate,</hi> but alwayes confeſſing his crime: and declaring howe his mothers Ghoaſt appeared vnto hym, vniſhed his ſpeedie deſtruction. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer offering his heatheniſhe ſacrifice by the han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of his Southſayers, he wylled them to call vp his mothers ſoule, and to make attonement betweene hir and hym, that he might liue in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eace &amp; reſt, Richarde the thirde king of Englande of that name, who with great tyranny came to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, murdering not onely his enimyes, <note place="margin">Richard the third.</note> but ſuche as had beene hys faythfull aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants: neyther ſparing his Nephews king Edwarde ſonnes nor his owne wife, but imbruing himſelfe in bloud on euery ſide, that hee mighte ſette hym ſelfe ſure in hys
<pb facs="tcp:6659:22"/> Throne. When he came to a vilage cales Boſworth not far from <hi>Leyceſter,</hi> where he ment to encounter his enemies. The ſame wente that the mghte before the fielde was ſought, he had a dreadfull &amp; terrible dreme. For it ſéemed to him being a ſléepe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaw diuers Images like terrible deuilles, which pulled and haled him, not ſufferinge him to take any quiet or reſt. The whithe ſtraunge viſion not ſo ſtroke his harte wiſh a ſuddayne feare, as it ſtuffed his head and troubled his minde with many buſie infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. For incontinent after, his harte being almoſt damped, he pregnoſticated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the doubtfull chaunce of the battalle to come, not vſing ſuch chearefulneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of mind and countenaunce as he was accuſtomed to doe before he came towarde the battayle. Wherevnto <hi>Polidore</hi> addeth <note place="margin">Polido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus virg. angli. hiſt. lib. 25.</note> thys fitte and excellent Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>I verily thinke this was no dreme, but a punction and ſting of of his ſinfull Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which being ſo much more wounded, as the offence is more heynous in degree, which ſurely if at any other time, yet princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally at the hower of death, it calleth freſhly to our rememberaunce miſchiefes con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icted
<pb facs="tcp:6659:22"/> and paynted forth before our eyes, puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes imminent, ſo that in the momente of death we are pricked in ſpirite for oure euell life and euen then we depart this world with intollerable vexation and griefe. Moyſes</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raly doth moſt liuely expreſſe the miſery of a guity Conſcience after this maner. <hi>And thy life ſhall hang before thee, and thou ſhalt feare both night and day, and ſhalt haue no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of thy life. In the morning thou ſhalt ſay, would God it were euening, and at the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueuing thou ſhalt ſay would Got it were morninge, for the feare of thine harte which thou ſhalte feare, Deut. 28.</hi> Howe breefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and playnely doeth <hi>Moyſes</hi> paynte oute the dayly, and continuall ſtraites and ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of a troubled Conſcience. Semblably ſpeaketh <hi>Saluſt</hi> of <hi>Cateline, For that impure minde of his, deteſted of God and man, could not be quieted night nor day. Therefore his couloure was pale and wanne, his eyes were foule and his pace ſometime ſwift, ſometime ſlow, in his face and countenaunce there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared Tiranny.</hi> To this ende ſerueth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> out of the booke of the <hi>Origin</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> world, where <note place="margin">Adam &amp; Eue.</note> 
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> wryteth that our firſt parentes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their tranſgreſſion, did hide them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:6659:23"/> and ſhonne the ſighte of God, theire feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſcience without all doubte condein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, therevnto accordeth that in the ſame booke, of <hi>Ioſephes</hi> bretheren fearing <note place="margin">Ioſeph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s bretheren.</note> leſte now theire Father being deade, he would remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruell dealing with him and reuehge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>id euen ſo was it with the traytor Iudas who weary of his life: by meanes of a wounded Conſcience, <note place="margin">Iudas.</note> ſtrangled himſelfe. But I ceaſe from ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering any moe examples, for it is moſte euidente that as the ſincere Conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the greateſt ſorrowes and miſeries of this world, miniſtreth an incredible ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and as it were taſte of the heauenly bliſſe, ſo the impure and corrupte Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; recordeth his guiltes and tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, tormenteth man in this worlde: and in ſome maner repreſenteth vnto him the furies ſorrowes and cruell tormentes of Hell. And as we ſee it come to paſſe in thoſe that haue bene incombred with a long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, albeit they dye at their appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted tyme, yet lyuing they ſéeme to dye ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely, rather then to lyue, ſo it fareth with the gaulled minde, and ſcared conſcience, albeit they ſhall periſhe euerlaſtingly, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6659:23"/> they repent, yet they cannot vpon this earth go ſkotfree, but receiue a taſte of their appointed fayre in the worlde to come.</p>
               <p>Nowe if a merie and contented minde (according to the wiſe mans ſaying) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth <note place="margin">Pro. 17. An vnquiet Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tience haſheneth old age, &amp; ſyckneſſe.</note> a floriſhing age, and if a ſorrowfull ſpirite dryeth the bones, it cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be, but the inward agony of the mind, breaketh out into the body, as well impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the health, as the ſtrength thereof. The Philoſophers and Phiſitions, holde this opinion, that through auxitie &amp; griefe of minde man pyneth awaye, waxeth olde quickly, and is taken away with vntimely death. And therfore they preſcribe in their dyets and ordery vſuals, that all men deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of manye yeares and long lyfe, ought to auoyde great penſiueneſſe and gréeuous cares as cauſe thereof. Whereby it maye eaſely appeare, howe peſtelent and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a plague it is, which weakeneth and in the ende vtterly deſtroyeth bodye and minde, whereof <hi>Fabius</hi> ſpeaketh excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if I can Iudge anye thing in this wyſe. <hi>There is nothing ſo buſied and variable, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſo rent and torne with dyuers affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as is the euill and vncleane minde. For</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6659:24"/> 
                  <hi>when it attempteth anye thing, it is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſtract with hope care and labor, and atchiuing his deſire, it is wrong and racked with carefulnes, fearefulnes, and an expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">An euell Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ayde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ery bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>of al miſchief.</hi> The ſame is confirmed by the holy Father S. <hi>Ambroſe, The corrupte Conſcience, ſtarteth at euery cracke, and the raw woundes cannot be corrected, with any playſter, whatſoeuer it heareth red or ſpoken, it accounteth as ſpoken againſte it ſelfe. If a man eate, if he ſtudye, if he praye, his crime is ſtraighte waye before him, the Conſcience witneſſeth agaynſt him, pleadeth againſt him condemneth him.</hi> Which thing conſidered by the Prophete, cauſed him to ſpeake in <note place="margin">The horcor of an euell Conſcience</note> this ſort. <hi>The wicked are lyke the raging of the Sea that cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt vp mire and dyrte, there is no peace ſayth the Lorde to the wicked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The heathen wryting of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he manifolde tormentes of Hell, ſpake of the rauening byrde called a Gryffon, which ſhould gnaw vpon mans lyuer, by the which they ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e nothing elſe but the gnawing of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, mangling as it were manne wyth dreadfull remembrances of euill, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this lyfe. Of a verie lyke opinion are
<pb facs="tcp:6659:24"/> ſome Deuynes, who thinke that men ſhall abyde the greeuous torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Hel, in their Conſcience which our Sauiour calleth the <hi>worme, gnawing the conſcience of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, neuer dying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as that opinion of theirs is not true, that the <hi>paynes of Hell are tollerated in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">All yartes ſhalbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cd and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in Apell.</note> 
                  <hi>conſcience onely.</hi> For out of doubt, al parts of man, internall and externall, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly abide vntollerable payne: ſo I will not denie but that to other tormentes, thys of the conſcience is added, as a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall weight or heape: whereby with great bytterneſſe of minde the wicked recogniſe, and ſet as it were preſent before their eics, their foule facts and deteſtable deedes done in their lyfe.</p>
               <p>And to ſhutte vp this matter, whereas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayth is the vnely Inſtrument, whereby <note place="margin">An exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationte beware of an euell Conſcience</note> man obteyneth iuſtification and immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, which can not be liuely in anye man, hauing a guplly conſcience: hereby we may cafely gather, how detcſtable and horrible a miſchiefe that is. Therefore whoſoeuer ſéeketh ſaluation by faith: it ſtandeth them vpon to brydle their affonions and conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences: and to commyt nothing againſt
<pb facs="tcp:6659:25"/> the commaundements of God. For he that tranſgreſſeth his conſcience accuſing hym, howe can he perſwade himſelfe, that God will be mercyfull vnto him. The faythfull in déede nowe and then ſtumble and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, it cannot be denied, but oute of all doubt, a true and lyuely fayth, hath no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the workes of darkeneſſe. Moreouer ſeing that death in it ſelfe of all terrible thinges is moſt terrible: it muſt néedes be much more horrible in thoſe who through the accuſation of their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: looke for a ſpéedie paſſage into hell tormentes. For natheleſſe doath it ſelfe is not ſo terrible as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugſome opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for euen thereafter as the conſcience is good or badde, ſo doth ſhee wyllingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace or dreadfully eſchewe the ſame. The godly receyue death wyllingly and gladly, which they knowe to be ſent vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from God as a delyuerance and paſſage, out of the miſeries of this troubleſome worlde, into the porte of eternall reſt, but the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked declyne the ſame as the perillous rocks and ſandes, where they muſt needes make ſhypwracke of eternall lyfe. Therefore it was truely and comfortably uttered by a
<pb facs="tcp:6659:25"/> certaine writte. We haue no cauſe to feare any thing in death, if our life haue not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any thing procuring cauſe of feare. For it is not poſſible that he ſhould dye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitently that hath lyued well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That a pure Conſcience is to be reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all humane actions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a man may content hymſelfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE AS there are manye thinges <note place="margin">The So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace and comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of a good Conſcience.</note> notably written by <hi>Cicero,</hi> which argue his great wiſedome and knowledge, yet amongeſt them all hath he left no ſaying more excellent and deuine then that in his booke intituled <hi>Of olde age:</hi> to wyt. <hi>That a conſcience of a lyfe well ſpent, and a remembrance of many good deedes is a thing moſt comfortable.</hi> Which worthie and memorable ſentence, is not onely agréeable with the ſecret iudgement of anye good man: but is alſo conſonant to the opinions of auncient Sages and good
<pb facs="tcp:6659:26"/> Deuines, who with one mouth doe wich their voyces confirme the ſame. And it is worthy to be obſerued, that <hi>Tully</hi> maketh not a common perſon to vtter that ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cc, but <hi>Cato</hi> ſurnamed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Senſor,</hi> a vcric graue <note place="margin">Cato.</note> and wiſe father. Whoſe vprightneſſe in cyuill Regimc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, long experience in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affayres, worthie vertues, and ſinguler wiſedome, all the Romayne hyſtories doc at large propoſſe and expreſſe: <hi>Cato</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out al controucrſie ſpake ſo of his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, contenting himſelfe with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde teſtimonie, when he ſuſteyncd the checkes of his ſuperiors, the enuye of hys equalles, and the obloque of his inferiors, an vnthankfull rewarde for that hys vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelant and fatherly care for the proſperous and happie eſtate of his Citizens and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie men. And it were to be wiſhed that all men, whether they liue priuately or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, woulde in all their doinges ſet that paterne before their eyes, wherein they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding themſelues daylie, as it were in a cléere glaſſe, might euidently ſée what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefieth or blemiſheth their vocation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of lyfe.</p>
               <p>And that theſe things may be the better
<pb facs="tcp:6659:26"/> conſidered: it ſhall not be amiſſe perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly to open &amp; vnfolde the duetyes of ſome functions in the common weale, whereby men maye paſſe from the partes to the whole, and by a fewe to vnderſtande what is conuenient for all.</p>
               <p>Thou art called to be a Iudge, or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen an Arbyter to compoſſe controuerſies, <note place="margin">The part of a iudge.</note> ſée that therein thou doe nothing againſt law and conſcience reſpecting any perſon: Let neyther threttes, neyther flatterie draw thée one heare breadth from vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in that matter thou ought neyther to haue friend nor enimie, Cooſen nor ſtraunger. For all theſe thinges ought to be ſet a ſide in iudgement. Yeelde noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fauour nor conſanguinitie: nothing to hatred or diſpleaſure, nothing to hope or feare, which things commonly ſtricke men ſtarke blinde in iudgement: &amp; to be ſhort, ſuffer not anye affection to be of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, but conſider the lawe, and moderate the ſame, if it be extréeme with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. So did good <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> who appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a daies man betwéene two men, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one to the ende he might drawe him into diſpleaſure with his aduerſarie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb facs="tcp:6659:27"/> many impertinent thinges: as that his aduerſarie had alſo much accuſed <hi>Ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tides. Well ſayth the Arbiter, omyt at thys tyme theſe matters, and alleage onely thoſe thinges wherein he hath abuſed thee. Cato</hi> alſo as <hi>Valerius</hi> reporteth, ſitting in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon a wicked and infamous <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> receyuing <hi>Pompeius Magnus</hi> his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters commendatorie in the behalfe of the malefactor: would not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The good Iuſticer would rather folow his owne internal iudgement, then obteyn thankes of that mightie man: teaching by his example that a Iudge ought not by any requeſt, rewarde or fauour, to be led from the true execution of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are called in anye ſtate to be <note place="margin">The part of a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and Cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne.</note> of the priuie counſayle, ought to direct all their conſultations to the helth and wealth of their countriemen: And albeit he ſée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes preſent daunger with floudes of enuy and malyce, together with falſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moures, &amp; vniuſt ſuſpitions of his doinges, yet let him not follow vayne fame, which neyther profiteth the euill, neyther hurteth the good: but the iudgemente of his conſcience as it were a guide and
<pb facs="tcp:6659:27"/> Lodeſman in all his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Neyther would I haue any man to miſtake me, as though I ment that we ſhould altogether neglect what the worlde thinketh and ſpeaketh of vs (which minde ought to be farre from a chriſtian for we ought not onely to avoyde euell, but to be far from all ſuſpicions of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, but I ſaye principally and chiefly our Conſcience is to be reſpectted. Yet we ſée the contrary in theſe dayes to vſuall, &amp; that ſaying euery where verified, <hi>Multi famam pauci conſcientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verent, verentur. Many te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their owne fame and credite but very few theire Conſcience.</hi> So <hi>Callicratides,</hi> a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of the Lacedemonians, hauing grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſpect of his priuate glory, then of hys Conſcience, in preſeruing of his Nauy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a great ouerthrowe of the enemy. <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> alſo fearing enuy onely, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered raſhly with <hi>Epaminondas</hi> and became almoſte an vtter ruine to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redemonians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard plantaginate</hi> duke of yorck becauſe he would not ſéeme to be incloſed and kept in his Caſtle of Sandale by a woman, and reſting only vpon his credite and fame, hee hauing not aboue fiue thouſand men, raſhly
<pb facs="tcp:6659:28"/> ioyned battayle with the Quéene, hauing xviij. M. good ſouldyers, contrary to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, wiſedome and al pollicy, and ſo raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ronne into his deſtruction. <hi>Q. Fabius Maximus</hi> after warde of his dooinges ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the Delair, more diſcretely handled the matter who in that tottering time of his country, abſtayned for a ſeaſon from fight with Hannibale, nothing accoump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the peoples obloquies, who called him a timerous man and a towarde, being in déede a right valiaunt man, and a ſtoute warriour, but contented himſelfe with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer conſideration of his own counſailes, of whome Ennius writeth thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnus homo nobis cunctando reſtituit rem Non ponebatenim rumores ante Salutem.</hi> And aſſuredly if Fabius: had not ſo done, the ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi> had then vtterly ben ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. And therefore hee reſted vpon his owu Conſcience, and not vpon populare rumoures, &amp; liked rather that men ſhould ſpèake euell of his wiſe regimente, then with their fauourable acclamations, to, caſt away himſelfe and indanger his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>The Sages of the Lawe beinge called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue
<pb facs="tcp:6659:28"/> out their opinions and ſpéeth, nyther <note place="margin">The office of good Lawyers.</note> touching the righte iudgement of caſes, or of factes and déedes done, maye not ſéeke to ſpeake pleaſantly but ſincerely, they ought not to diſprayſe thinges commendable, nor commend thinges blameable, no not if hée be allured to the one with hope of great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and gayne, or drawen from the other with greate terrors and daungers. Suche <note place="margin">Papinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> a Lawyer was Papinianus of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure Antonius his counſayle, who being deſired; &amp; afterward with terrible threats commaunded to defend the Emperours ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranous facte, in murdering his yong bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Geta</hi> euen in his mothers lappe, was willing rather to abide death, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake thinges contrarie to the law of nature and of al nations, anſwering Antonius franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>O Emperoure it is more eaſie to commit paricide then to defend it:</hi> Suche another <note place="margin">Sir Iames Hales.</note> Lawyer was ſir <hi>Iames Hales</hi> knight one of the iuſtices of the common place, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called by men of great power &amp; might, to ſubſcribe vnto a deuice for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſſenheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the then Lady Mary, &amp; Lady <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> would in no wiſe neither by curteous nor ſeuere ſpéeches be broughte vnto it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6659:29"/>
               <p>And afterwarde in the dayes of bloude, when all his fellowes changed their coates he at a quarter ſeſſions holden in <hi>Kente</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the lawe, and gaue charge vpon the ſtatutes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eyght and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixt, in derogation of the primacy of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For whiche cauſe his former fidelity forgotten, he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to pryſon, and there ſo terrifyed by the bloudy Prieſtes, that he alſo at the laſt would ſhew himſelfe a conformable man, whereby he was brought into the Quéenes preſence, and receiued wordes of grace and comfort, but alack whiles he obteyned this he loſeth gods grace and his guiding ſpirit: and the Diuell that capitall and auncient enimy of man, leadeth him vnto a ſhallowe brooke within halfe a mile of his own dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, where he hauing no doubte a gauled Conſcience, for the ſhipwracke of his fayth lay downe groueling and with muche la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure drowned him ſelfe. His laſte fal and puniſhment ſuccéeding the ſame, doeth py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily enough perſwade men to auoyde ſuch declinations from Iuſtice, and to contend with al their powers and might to imitate the former notable and worthy déede of his
<pb facs="tcp:6659:29"/> in pronouncing what law and equitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, euen to thoſe that then were mighty and malicious enemies of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that be in authority and vſe the ſame, to hale and pull from the miniſterye, <note place="margin">Spotlers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the church.</note> landes and poſſeſſions giuen and left to the Church, by the liberality of our forefathers cannot but haue an vnquiet Conſcience, which albeit for a time it ſeeme to ſleepe, yet it will wake at the laſte, and to their great vexation will ſette before their eyes their rapine and ſpoyle, in degree nothing behinde deteſtable Sacrilege. Their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will one day tell them that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of now they cannot be ignorant: that theſe thinges were geuen of old toward the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of religion, and to the needeful vſes of the Church, to mainteyne Paſtors, Preachers, Doctors, and interpreters of Gods law, to bréede and bring vp yong Plantes that may in time, become fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trees, in Gods orcharde, as well in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching pure doctrine, as in confounding he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis.</p>
               <p>And to conuerte ſuche thinges to ſatiſfie priuate auarice, rape, greedines, &amp; vanity, what other thing can it be then moſte hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb facs="tcp:6659:30"/> impiety and wickednes. It auayleth them very litle to ſay that thoſe goods haue béene abuſed, or that in the beginning they were dedicate to idolatrous vſes, it is an old and good ſaying, <hi>propter abuſum, res non tollenda,</hi> that thinges neceſſary and prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are not to be taken away for the abuſe ſake only. And if we haue thought it hereto fore vnlawful &amp; vngodly to abuſe the goods of the Church in pompe and pleaſure (as in déede they haue béene, which all good men lament) let vs think it more intollerable &amp; impius, to make thoſe things priuat which before were publique: and to tranſferre them from deuine, to prophane vſes. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the exchange of the poſſeſſors, <hi>Luther</hi> that worthy man was wont fynely to ſay, that theſe goods, were ſometime geuen to Aſſes and Swine, meaning rude monkes and Godleſſe Epicures, and now at the laſt they returne to like perſons agayne, ſurely he ſpake rightly: for excepte a fewe, ſuch goods haue ben a pray to hunters, foulers, and ſuch like. But God (ſuch is his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and iuſt dealings, although ſecrete) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not theſe breakers of deade mens wils and teſtamentes, to haue theirs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6659:30"/>
               <p>For commonly ſuche fathers doe deliuer like children, who being Coggers, foyſters, and at the laſt banckeroute: inioy not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in the third diſſente, goods ſo racked and drawn together. As for their dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to prophane vſes, it is no new obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the aunſwere ſhapen of olde maye yet ſerue to wit that idolatry ceaſſing thoſe goods ought to bee imployed to the vſe of Chriſtes church, euen as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour tooke the eccleſiaſticall gooddes of the Donatiſtes and beſtowed them vpon the Catholick church, wherof when the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes complained as of great wrong and iniury offred by the catholiques. S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> afterward defended the fact, and aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them. That thoſe goods in déede, were the churches, and might well by the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our maieſtrate, bee taken from thoſe that were no members of the ſame, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the right owners, to wit the Church onely.</p>
               <p>Theſe poſſeſſions and donacions then do <note place="margin">In whome the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of church goods doth teſte.</note> appertaine neither to the Prince, nor to the Prieſt, nor to the people perticulerly, but to the whole church and their property can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:6659:31"/> by any meanes be chaunged. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> bought all the ſubſtaunce of the Egiptions to the houſe of <hi>Pharao,</hi> but the landes and fieldes of the Prieſtes he touched not. <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. The reaſon is giuen in another place, That amongs other priuileges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy their goods ſhould neuer be allienated from them, for that their groundes are a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall poſſeſſion. <hi>Num.</hi> 25. Therefore the bleſſed martir <hi>Laurence</hi> led by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy ghoſt, would not deliuer <hi>Decius</hi> the Emperoure <note place="margin">Backbiters and ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye.</note> the treaſure of the Church. Theſe gréedye worldlinges when the matter will not ſupport then, turne to the perſons, and they ſaye that miniſters are idle and liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out laboure, that they are couetous and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicious: therfore the leſſe portions will ſerue them, and thereby their mindes will not be ſo buſied about worldly affaires, and therewithall they ought to be contente, for humility and pouerty ſay they, is the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers profeſſion and ſuch doth our ſauioure pronounce bleſſed and happy.</p>
               <p>What idlencſſe and wante of laboure ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt miniſters liue in, God knoweth, but it may truely be ſayd of moſte of them that their ſtudy which Epicures call idleneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:31"/> conſumeth the ſtrength of the body, and weareth the very ſoule, as all that put the ſame in vre can teſtify. And as for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice and couetouſeneſſe of the Preachers let that fault touch ſome, but it cannot bée verifyed of the moſte part: For dayly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, in the country abrode, letteth them ſee miniſters, widdowes, and orphaynes, to haue ſcarce ſufficient to pay their credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and to hire them a cotage to hide them in, from ſtorms and tempeſtes: be it that a few of the clergy in place of honor prouide better. But not onely the poore country miniſter, but alſo the doctor in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Churches, haue lefte thoſe whome God willed them to care for, in no better e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate then I haue ſayde, power and habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not ſeruing them any better. Is this the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that great gréedineſſe which ſo much gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth theſe contemners of Gods worde and of his miniſters?</p>
               <p>Now in that they will haue miniſters, and preachers, to follow with Friers wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pouerty: beſides that they do violence to the holy ſcripture, which ſpeaking of a Chriſtian and Godly life, generally theſe good men forſoth maye not abide that thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:6659:32"/> precepts ſhould be extended to their bellies but to the pore miniſters only, they alſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> who taking from pore Chriſtians their goods and liuinges, told them that it was theire profeſſion if a man tooke their coates, to giue him their cloakes alſo, with ſuche prety conceites, doe theſe Hypocrites ſporte them ſelues, and ſpoyle the pore miniſtery of their dew and lawfull liuelehode.</p>
               <p>But ſome forſooth can not abyde ſuche extremity, they will haue the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poralities only as they cal them, that is they wil haue the Royaltie, &amp; the miniſters ſhall haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries: And would god they would leaue Chriſtes church, but to ſerue euen neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but according to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proueth. <hi>They giue a flee, and take a Cammell, they leaue a louſe and take an horſe.</hi> It were good for them to haue in remembraunce the old ſaying: <hi>It is a deſtruction for a man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that which is ſanctified, and after the vowes to inquire. Pro.</hi> 20. Of the which you may réede further in <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. Leuit. 22. Mala.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that haue the Tutell or wardſhip <note place="margin">The office and duty</note> of yong Gentlemen, oughte to vſe their
<pb facs="tcp:6659:32"/> landes and liuinges, and chiefely their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils <note place="margin">of Patron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> toward their wards</note> in good education, as they may with a ſincere Conſcience, giue a reckening there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of another day, both before God and man. But nowe a dayes the number is greate of thoſe that more reſpect their owne gayne, then the good guyding of their pupilles, ſo that ſimple and weake infancy, wanteth not her vnderminers, <hi>Demoſtenes</hi> compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth muche of his Tutors, that they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed his parentes goods guilefully, and reſpected nothing his good education. Such a Tutor was <hi>Richard</hi> duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> of whoſe life and death I haue ſpoken ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what &amp; therefore wil be the ſhorter in this matter.</p>
               <p>It is much to be lamented, that wardes in England are as commenly bought and ſolde, as are brute beaſtes and Cattell, and vngodly mariages often times made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene eyther infantes, or ſuch as be of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeares, who before they come to theire <note place="margin">Of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of wardes.</note> mature time of diſcertion, are led by other mens eyes and hartes, to that, will they nill they, which liketh not them but their Guerdons &amp; Tutors. Whereby it fauleth out moſt commonly, that thoſe that are lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:6659:33"/> together in ſuch wiſe with formal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimomes, and ceremoinall, rather then materiall, doe not loue, but mortally hate, and deteſt ech other, whome neuer liking loue of lawful matrimony, but greedy gain forcibly coupled and comoyned. Dayly deuorces and often murders iuſuing ſuche ſuppoſed mariages in this our country, ſheweth forthy incommodity of the ſame: but eſpecially is moſt lamentable that our law is nere repugnaunt to the dinne law, which in ſemblable caſes permitteth to ech party frée election, but there is good hope, that ſuch as be in authority wil alſo reform this thing ſo farre out of all good forme.</p>
               <p>Their diuers and ſundry good prouiſions in all other matters, biddeth vs lóoke for the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in this, which God graunt.</p>
               <p>To deſcend to leſſe matters, let men in <note place="margin">Of by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts &amp; ſcllers.</note> bying and ſelling, reſpect their Conſcience, and not follow peruerſe cuſtome, let them thinck that there is no good gayne, where playne dealing hath no place. And to omit thoſe that ſell not their wares, according to their valure, but for as muche as they can: doe we thinck that thoſe men reſpect theire Conſcience, that mingle their wares and
<pb facs="tcp:6659:33"/> corrupt the ſame. For example y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther ſelling wine with-water for pure wine &amp; couſloring, els mingle his wines, cannot haue herein a good and honeſte meaning. <hi>Anacharſis</hi> ſayd truely, the Market to be a ſet place for <hi>Fraude</hi> and <hi>Rapine,</hi> meaning that men in buying and ſelling had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of a good Conſcience. It were neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in contractes for men, not onely ſpeak to nothing ſauing truth, but alſo that they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceile not from the byer any faultes, of ſuch thinges as they ſell.</p>
               <p>We muſt no doubt decline from al things that agree not with the internal iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the conſcience, &amp; therefore <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an</hi> in the Digeſtes writeth grauely. <hi>That euen the lawe of nature commaundeth vs not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our ſubſtance, with other mens loſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thoſe men are much worſe; who in <note place="margin">Agaynſt raſh and bayn ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> their othes vſe againſt al right iudgement, a kinde of peruerſe ſubtilty, and wilyneſſe, not onely abuſing their Conſcience, but ſcorming Gods holy name. Such fraude was practiſed by one of thoſe ten captiues, whom after the fiew foughten at Canmas, <hi>Anniball</hi> ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> for the exchange of Priſoners: taking their oath only, for their
<pb facs="tcp:6659:34"/> returne, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had taken their loue of <hi>Anniball</hi> and departed the Campe, one of <note place="margin">The God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſleights and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iftes of many to illude the it othes.</note> them by and by retourneth back ſaying that hée had forgotten ſomthing behind him and ſuppoſing by that ſleight his oth to bée ſatiſfied, hée ſpéedeth him ſelf in his iorney, and ouertaketh his fellowes before night. Now when theſe ten could not draw to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Concluſion in the Senate houſe, they al retourned to <hi>Anniball</hi> ſauing that one who thought that by ſuch guilful meanes, he had diſcharged himſelf.</p>
               <p>Which thing when the Senate had kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of, they cauſed him to be apprchended and ſent vnto <hi>Anniball. Cicero</hi> ſayth that this was an illuſion, and no good interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his oth, for fraud and Guile doth bynde and not diſolue penurye. It was then nothing elſe but a péeuiſh wilineſſe peruerſly imitating Prudence and Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anniball</hi> himſelfe at what time hée had taken <note place="margin">Anniball.</note> truce with the <hi>Romaynes,</hi> for forty dayes: in the night time hée ſpoyled the fieldes, and when the league was aleaged he aunſwered that he had not broken the ſame, which extended only to the day and
<pb facs="tcp:6659:34"/> not to the night. The like we may reade in <hi>Plutarch</hi> of <hi>Cleomenes,</hi> in <hi>Strabo</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cleome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> Such practiſes are red euen of Popiſh Prelates, who with fraudulent interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of their othes haue ſucked the bloud of thoſe that repoſed all fayth in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted their liues vnto their protection.</p>
               <p>At what time <hi>Lewis</hi> king of <hi>Fraunce</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Adelbartus</hi> an Exle in the Caſtle of <hi>Bamberge,</hi> which by meanes of the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius cituacion, and good furniture of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, could by no meanes be gotten: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he ſaw the lions ſkinne would not auayle, he put vppon a Woulues ſkinne, leauing manhoode, &amp; practiſing ſubtilty. The king then ſent a Biſhop vnto the Earle, to moue him to come to ſome Parle with the King: giuing him his faith that he would reduce <note place="margin">A popiſhe Prelates feaude.</note> him ſafe and ſound into his Caſtle againe. The Earle was ſoone perſwaded and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to goe with the biſhop. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had not paſſed many paces out of the Caſtle gate. Were it not good ſaid the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late for vs to eate a morſel of meate before we go vnto the king, with a good will quod the Earle, and ſo retourned vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Caſtle
<pb facs="tcp:6659:35"/> to duiner agayn, After meate they aroſe and came to the King, who immediately <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> cauſed the Earle to be apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted.</p>
               <p>Now when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Earle ſaw he muſt néedes dye, he complayned of breach of fayth and trothe: vnto whom the Biſhop made this aunſwere. That he performed his promiſe in that hée brought him ſafe and ſound into his Caſile to eate meat, and for that hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed not his promiſe afterward, he could not hée charged with violating of his oth. <note place="margin">Ottho Phringen ſis.</note> The recorder of this matter putteth down his own iudgement of the deede, in this wiſe. <hi>Let other men iudge of this Prelate, what they liſt, as though it were done for the peace, and quietneſſe of the whole Lande. But for my own part I thus thinck, that no Chriſtian ought once to conceaue any ſuche thought, eſpecially in ſo great a matter of life and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ende of this Prelate was fearefull &amp; ſtraunge afterward, when the Elements moſt terribly ſeemed with fyre to burne, and with noyſe to be confounded together the mighty. God ſtrack him with his Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt and ſo hée miſerably dyed: who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:6659:35"/> examineth his own Conſcience and ſecret iudgement, ſhall ſoone ſée that ſuch fleightes procéede of an vnhoneſt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious pollicy, méere contrary to nature, beeing moſt ſhamefull and vile for any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall man but once to thincke vpon, much leſſe to put the ſame in any execution. For Nature her ſelfe deſireth thinges that bée right and iuſt, and deſpiſeth the contrary: neyther will ſhe hermit commodity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out honeſty, to haue any place with her. So <hi>Ioſua</hi> kept the league and truce taken with the <hi>Sabonites,</hi> notwithſtanding their fraud and circumuention, neither would hée by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes breake his fayth and trouth gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto them.</p>
               <p>Albeit there is ſome diuerſity of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> bouites.</note> among the learned, whether <hi>Ioſua</hi> did wel or not, in ſparing thoſe people both whome God commannded him to deſtroy, and alſo of whome hée was circumuented, and deceiued in making of the league. For hée ſéemed not to hée bounde by anye Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to kéepe that fayth which he gaue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued with their Guile, &amp; that vnto Gods enemies. Theſe things ſéeme ſomedeale hard to be diſcuſſed. Firſt of all <hi>Ioſua</hi> could
<pb facs="tcp:6659:36"/> not be ignoraunt, that all thoſe people, that dwelled in the Land of <hi>Promiſe</hi> ought by Gods commaundement, vtterly to be rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out. But that the <hi>Gabaonites</hi> did inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit any part of that land he wiſt not. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore albeit in ſome reſpect for ignoraunce, <hi>Ioſua</hi> might ſéeme to pretend excuſe: for that the <hi>Gabaonites</hi> comming with their olde ſhoes, and torne Garments, abuſed him, feyning them ſelues to be people that came from far: yet he cannot auoyd blame both for his ouermuch ſecurity and creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and alſo for his negligence, in that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manner, he inquired not at Gods mouth what was conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for him to doe.</p>
               <p>There be ſome that goe about to loſe this knot after this maner. That <hi>Ioſua</hi> did both execute Gods commaundement, and alſo that he well performed his promiſe. For whiles he ſuffereth them to liue he offereth the better, and in that he maketh them ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill <note place="margin">Ambroci us in offi.</note> men, he executeth the firſt, for <hi>Vlpian</hi> in the <hi>Digeſts</hi> compareth perpetuall ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude with death. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, <hi>Ioſua</hi> aſked not the Lords will, by meane of to moch credulty, which commonly al playn
<pb facs="tcp:6659:36"/> and good natures haue in them, &amp; hée addeth this fine and golden ſentence. <hi>So holy and reuerend was fayth in thoſe dayes, that collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and fraude was rarely ſounde amongſte men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is then the cauſe why <hi>Ioſua</hi> tooke peace and truce with the <hi>Cabaonites.</hi> Now that he killed them not deprehending their Euile, but brought them in ſeruitude: was becauſe he woulde not breake his worde bound with an oth: leſſe in blaming other mens vnfaythfulneſſe, hée ſhould ſéeme to incurre the ſame fault himſelfe. Hée ſaued their liues therefore; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee made them ſlaues: his ſentence conteyned mercy, but ſhe long puniſhment had in it ſeuerity, and thus far S. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others write hereof in this wiſe. Wée gather that god accepted and ratified <hi>Ioſua,</hi> his oth giuen to the <hi>Gabaonites,</hi> not in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he liked fraud and Guile, but that their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſire, and ſubmiſſion pleaſed him. For <note place="margin">Lauaterus in Ioſ. 9. P. Martir in 2. Sam. 21.</note> firſt God promiſed <hi>Ioſua</hi> to be with him in reſkewing and defending of the Citie <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baon.</hi> Secondly, when <hi>Saule</hi> had cauſed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of theſe <hi>Gabaonyttes</hi> to be murdered, contrarie to this promiſe of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> made
<pb facs="tcp:6659:37"/> vnto their aunceſtors, God was angrle and ſent a famine among the Iſraelites, which continued by the ſpace of three yeres, neyther coulde his wrath be mitigated, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll ſuch tyme as ſeauen of <hi>Saules</hi> ſonnes, or neereſt kinſmen were hanged: It is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible that Gods ſpeciall pleaſure was to haue the <hi>Gabaonyttes</hi> preſerued. And it is lykely that <hi>Ioſua</hi> being a Prophete, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode ſo much: Mine owne iudgement is this, That whereas the chiefe cauſe whye the Lord God would haue the inhabitants of that country deſtroyed was: leſte they might afterward draw the Iſraelites from the true worſhipping of the lyuing God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> declareth in <hi>Deutero. &amp; Num. 22.</hi> Theſe <hi>Gabaonyttes</hi> whom the ſecond booke of kings, accounteth among the Amdrits, were both humble and lowly, and alſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to imbrace the Religion of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> moued there vnto with the fame of Gods great miracles, and wunders which he ſhewed in defending and preſeruing the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Egipt,</hi> in the wildernes and about <hi>Iordayn,</hi> for ſo them ſelues confeſſed, <hi>Ioſua</hi> therefore ſpared their liues, but tooke from them their liberty: whereby he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:6659:37"/> all occaſions of auerting the Iſraelites from the liuing God to be remooued away: and ſo hée imbaſing them and weakning them with ſeruitude, kept him ſelfe pure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpot of infamous periury, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Atheiſme, wherewithall the Godleſſe people with ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mouthes would haue moſt ſhamefully blotted him.</p>
               <p>The fact of <hi>Ioſua</hi> therefore is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, and letteth vs ſee what regard men ought to haue of Leagues, and truces confirmed with othes betwéene them and their enemies, contrary to the vnconſtante dealinges of the <hi>Romaines</hi> in times paſt, and the french Catholiks, in this our time. For the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> did violate and break the League taken with the <hi>Samllites</hi> and confirmed with ſolemne othes of their Conſulles. <hi>T. Veturius, Caluirius,</hi> and <hi>Sp. Poſtumius Albinus.</hi> Suppoſing that their othe was diſcharged, when they had delyuered the ſayde Conſulles backe into the <hi>Samnyttes</hi> handes, to be handled at their pleaſures: ſo that it is ſayde of one no leſſe finely then truely. <hi>If the Romaines had</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The peritt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>kept like faith with the Samnites, which they exacted of other: eyther they had not remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:6659:38"/> at al, eyther elſe they had ſerued the Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyttes.</hi> And not much vnlyke was their dealings, with the <hi>Numantynes.</hi> Whereby it is moſt euident that the Romaines dyd <note place="margin">Auguſt dei viu ita te dei lib. cap. 22.</note> not alwayes ſo preciſely keepe their fayth holye and vnbroken, as ſome would ſéeme to importe. Although I ſée what may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in their behalfe: to wyt, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions or articles take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwéene the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaines are ſo far forth to be obſerued on both partes, as the ſuperioure magiſtrate (which was the Senate among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines)</hi> aſſenteth ther vnto. So ſay they the concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of peace made by <hi>Mancinus</hi> the Conſull, with the <hi>Numantines</hi> was of no moment, the whole Senate miſlyking the ſame. And ſo <hi>Camillus</hi> would not ſtand to <note place="margin">Camillus.</note> the conditions of peace, which the Senate made with the french men, without his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent being dictator or chiefe officer. Which aunſweres or rather fryuolous excuſes, I will not now examine: only I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ke that ſaying of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> worthy remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>Romulus and the Romayne ſtock haue ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iuſtinius. liber. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>with wolues milke, wolues condicions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And touching the Tragicall doings of the Catholiques of late in the realme of
<pb facs="tcp:6659:38"/> 
                  <hi>Fraunce,</hi> what tonge or pen can ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">The late tragical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aunce.</note> ſet forth the ſame. Surely all poſterities wil abhor and deteſt ſuch infidelity, ioyned with barbarouſe cruelty, when they ſhall réede in hiſtories of Edicts, &amp; decrées, made in Parlaments, of leagues &amp; truces, taken and confirmed betwéene party and party, with ſolemne conteſtation of Gods moſt reuerende maieſtie: of moſt aſſured and intéere frendſhip, peace, amity, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, with an vtter obliuion of all former quarels, and diſpleaſures. Where vpon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued Ambaſſages Gratulatory, from great and mighty Princes round about: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages betwéene great eſtates on eyther party, moſt ſtrongly to vnite and knit this knot of frendſhip: and not withſtanding all theſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midle of paſtimes and triumphes to murder ſo many graue fathers and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, ſuch ſéemely and comly gentlemen and gentlewomen in their beds; that had repoſed them ſelues in the fayth and troth of their Prince, ſo many ſucking babes in their cradels, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were not able to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the right &amp; wrong, is ſuch an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day hath not ben heard of. Surely it is expreſſely agaynſt that law of warre,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:39"/> appoynted by God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. Which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner. <hi>If thou ſhalt come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecge any cittie, thou ſhalte firſte offer them peace, and if they accepte it, and open theire gates vnto thee, then ſhalte thou ſaue all the people of that Citty, and they ſhall ſerue thee and pay thee tribute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here the ſubiects yeld their goodes, their townes, yea their bodies into the hand of their Lord: &amp; yet we ſée what immanity was executed vpon them. Secondly al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to graunt to forreyn ennemies, the <note place="margin">The law dem to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyantes &amp; to ſuch as yeld them ſelues in war.</note> law of Suppliaunts, if they demaund it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. and therewithall not to touch the vnarmed multitude, as infants, yong folks auncient and aged perſonnes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. And ſo the <hi>Ethnucks</hi> did ſoundly kéepe the law of <hi>Suppliantes,</hi> and thought <hi>Iupiter</hi> to be the Patron of them, and reuenger of their ennemies, as the morall of that fable of <hi>Aeſope</hi> of the Eagle and <hi>Scarabaes</hi> doeth declare: but in <hi>Fraunce</hi> we ſee no conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this law, but a general hauock or bouchery to haue bene made of al ages, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and degrees, withoute anye difference at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pauſanias</hi> cyteth a worthy example of a
<pb facs="tcp:6659:39"/> plage that fel vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Acheans</hi> becauſe they <note place="margin">Pauſanias in Acha.</note> broke the law of Suppliants. <hi>When</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the Achayans drewe the ſuppliantes out of the Temple, Gods reuenging wrath was not ſloe nor prolonged againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for there happened a vehement and ſuddayne earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, which turned vp not onely the wales, but alſo the whole Citie, in ſuch ſort, that no ſignes thereof appeared.</hi> And the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> are much ſpoken againſt in hiſtories, becauſe they murdered the inhabitauntes, after they had yelded their Citty, and great miſeries and calamities came vpon them for ſuch vnmercifull dealinges.</p>
               <p>Out of al doubte Conqueſtes and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ought not to be inſolente and bloudy, <note place="margin">Conqueſtes ought to haue mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as a companion.</note> but modeſt and mercifull, as well for the eſtabliſhing of peace as for the conſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe which be vanquiſhed and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, it is a good ſaying. <hi>He that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mimus.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe in victory, is twiſe a Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour:</hi> Neyther may the victor repute him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out al peril. <hi>Agamemno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> is admoniſhed in <hi>Seneca:</hi> that he ſhould not vſe victories crewelly, vſeth this arrogant ſpéech: <hi>Wher of ſhould the conquerour be afrayd, Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> aunſwereth. <hi>Of that whiche he feareth
<pb facs="tcp:6659:40"/> not.</hi> That is to ſay, the victor ought to doute many ſuddayne chaunſes. And the ſame Author in Troade. When <hi>Pirrhus</hi> ſayde, <hi>No lawe commaundeth to ſpare captiues, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamemnon</hi> aunſwereth, <hi>That which lawe forbiddeth not, ſhamefaſtneſſe forbiddeth, Pirrhus. The victor may doe what him li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth: Agamemnon: That man ought to doe leſte, that he may do moſt.</hi> Wherfore <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelaus</hi> is much comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for his clemency, <note place="margin">Ageſelaus</note> for that in his orations he accuſtomed to admoniſh his ſouldyers, that they ſhoulde not handle their captiues cruelly, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to remember them to be men which were fallen into calamity: wherevnto men as long as they liue vpon earth are ſubiect. God hath purtured in the Lion a Picture <note place="margin">The proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of the Lyon.</note> of valiaunt warriers, for in the Lion there is not onely a ſtoute courage, conioyned with the ſtrength of body, but alſo an heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal clemency, toward ſuch as fal down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, according to that vearſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Percere proſtratis ſeit nobilis ira Leonis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A good warriour ought therefore to expres both their vertues, as Hirgil writeth moſt grauely.</p>
               <p>Percere ſubiectis &amp; debellare ſuperbos.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6659:40"/>
               <p>When one of <hi>Sigiſmundes</hi> counſayle, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulated <note place="margin">Sigiſmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> with him, for that he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon his ennimies liues and goods, whome he had taken, but receiued them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the number of frendes, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour aunſwered after this maner. <hi>Thou thinkeſt it good to kill thy ennemy, becauſe a dead man cannot bite, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb: But I do kil mine enemy whilſt I ſpare him crauing pardon: and doe make him my frende, in that I aduaunce him to credite.</hi> A notable wiſe ſaying no doubt of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. Lyke examples are founde in the auncient hyſtories of the Romaynes, who for that they did religiouſly kepe the lawe of Suppliants: written amongſt the alwes of Heralds: they adiorned vnto them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Princes and people in amitie &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe.</p>
               <p>But peraduenture ſome will aunſwere that the french Catholiques did not breake <note place="margin">S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</note> any law of armes in vſing pollicie againſt their enmmies, for ſaint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in hys queſtions vpon <hi>Ioſua</hi> ſayth. <hi>When warre is iuſt &amp; lawfull: he ſwerueth not from iuſtice that purſueth his enimies, either by ſtrength or pollicy.</hi> And euen ſo <hi>Antigonus,</hi> when
<pb facs="tcp:6659:41"/> one aſked him howe he ſhoulde deale with <note place="margin">Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> hys enimies, anſwered: <hi>Eyther with fraude or dinte of ſworde: eyther openly or ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> And <hi>Virgil. Dolus an virtus quis in hoſte requirat.</hi> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> alleageth that <note place="margin">Hier. in 17. Ezeh.</note> verſe as ſeculer, but liketh very well ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: ſo farre forth as no fayth &amp; troth geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be byolate. But I thinke the word <hi>Dolus</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verſe to be taken of honeſt and lawfull pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies in war: And that all ſubtill cauiláti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fraudes and periuries, are excepted. For the word no doubt ſignifieth <hi>Prudens Stratagema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The king of <hi>Denmarck</hi> vſing fraud and <note place="margin">The king of denmark his pollicy.</note> periury agaynſt his ſubiectes is much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended, for that when hee coulde not bring in by maine might, certaine perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious outlawes and pirates, hée brought it to paſſe by pollicy: for he pretending open war agaynſt forreyn enimies, ſommoned his men oſ war to come and ſerue him, and among the reſt ſent alſo vnto thoſe theeues both graunting them pardon for all theire offences committed agaynſt him, and alſo promiſed them for their ſeruice large and liberall wages, And when they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, he ſtraight way put them to death.
<pb facs="tcp:6659:41"/> Such pollicyes hauing periury anexed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them ought to be deteſted of al good men and chiefly of Princes, whome verity and conſtancy in words of promiſes, haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſingulerly commended.</p>
               <p>The french <hi>Stratagemes</hi> are not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the daniſh dealings, ſauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury was more heynous in Fraunce: for that the aduerſe part were already come in and had layd down their arniour and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, and had on their part giuen out infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible and euident ſignes, of their loue and fidelity to their Prince.</p>
               <p>The cruell deede of <hi>Peter Arrogon</hi> is much deteſted, who ſlew eyght thouſande <note place="margin">Peter Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogon.</note> french men in Cicil, for that they had ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed that Ile in his abſcnce, and yet he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſed his cruelty vpon forreyners and ſtraungers, but theſe vpon their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nere kinſnien, They ſeemed to haue ſet before their eyes the diſſimulation <note place="margin">A. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus.</note> of <hi>Antonius Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modus</hi> whoſe maners they haue exactly expreſſed: For when he was wearyed with filthy pleaſures, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he was exceedingly geuen, leſt he mighte ſéem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſpend tune in dooing nothing, hee
<pb facs="tcp:6659:42"/> deuyſed with him ſelfe how he might mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Nobles of his Empire: eſpecially he cauſed one Iulianus to be ſlayn ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and horribly in his bedde, and yet in the ſight of men he woulde kiſſe and embrace him, calling him his ſweete hart, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued father. Or hapely they looked nerer home, and bchelde the pollicies of ſome of <note place="margin">Carolus ſeptimus Gal rex.</note> their Aunceſtors. We reade of Charles the vy. king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> that after long and greeuous troubles in that country, he ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into league and affinity with the duke of <hi>Burgondy:</hi> and promiſed moſt conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bury all auncient quarrels and grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: &amp; ther vpon they both receiued at the prieſtes handes the hoſt conſecrated, as the manner was in thoſe dayes, in confyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their othes and promyſes, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, when as the ſayd king hadde inuited the duke to come to <hi>Montrell,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to entertayne him moſt frendely, and to exhibit vnto him ſpectacles and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, he ſuffered the duke to be murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vppon the bridge there, as they werein communication together.</p>
               <p>Some may aunſwere that how theſe <note place="margin">Nothing is protitable rule vnleſt it be honeſt.</note> men kept their fayth they wil not examin,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:42"/> but by theſe doinges there followed tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and quietneſſe vnto thoſe Regions, and country: I anſwere let it be ſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time, but if we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, the conſequence of ſuch truce breakings, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne cruelties, we ſhall finde in the ende vtter ſubuerſion to haue enſewed greate houſes, and families therefore. Surely all good men imbrace that ſaying, <hi>There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ariſtidea.</note> 
                  <hi>profitable vnleſſe it be alſo honeſt.</hi> And therefore <hi>Ariſtides</hi> did openly in the <note place="margin">Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocles.</note> audience of the people reiecte the polliticke counſell of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> concerning the burning of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> Nauy: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being profitable it was not thoughte honeſt, <hi>Furius Camillus</hi> receiued not the <note place="margin">F. Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</note> children of the Lords of <hi>Phalice,</hi> betrayed to him by their Schoolemaſter, but ſtripped him naked and deliuered him to be whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped home wyth roddes by the ſame Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>Kingly vertues in times paſt haue bene <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otes vertues.</note> reported to be theſe, Iuſtice, gentleneſſe, and clemencie: but crueltie, and outrage haue bene miſliked. <hi>Scipio</hi> hath in all ages bene prayſed, who was wonte to ſay, that he had rather ſaue one citezen, then ſley a
<pb facs="tcp:6659:43"/> thouſand enimies, which ſentence the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Antonius</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Pius</hi> did often repeate. Contrariwiſe it was a ſhamefull byworde vſed againſt yong <hi>Tiberius,</hi> to be called <hi>Clay tempered with bloud.</hi> It is no ſufficient allegation to ſay, that kings haue abſolute power of lyfe and death ouer their ſubiectes. There cannot be alleaged anye greater authoritie, then that the Dictators hadde at Rome, in whome was the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power of peace and warre, and of lyfe and death, and that without appeale. Yet might they not execute a Citiſen, hys cauſe vnheard, and without condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by order of law. Onely murderers and théeues doe take awaye mens lyues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order of law, without hearing the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie pleade his cauſe, and to ſpeake for hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but what neede many wordes. It is cléerer <note place="margin">The proper and eſpecial notes and ſignes of Papiſtes.</note> then the noone day, that cruelty, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, and filthie adulterie, are the verie proper noates and badges of Papiſtes in theſe our dayes.</p>
               <p>It is much to be lamented that the noble and famous Nacion of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhold learn of <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Turck,</hi> vnto whom they linck themſelues in legue to care for no promiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6659:43"/> fayth, or oth: and I pray God in the ende they be not ſcourged by Antichriſt, whom they truſt, and diſtruſt God, with whome whiles they ſeeke to concerue peace, and concorde, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not chuſe but be at diſcord and open warre with God. The old Poets doe feine that the proud Giauntes waged battaile agaynſte heauen, whereby they ment vndoubtedly, thoſe that deſpiſe laws and breake their oaths, moſt blaſphemouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſing Gods name. And thoſe that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily commit ſuch offences, the Deuel doth wholy poſſeſſe their harts by litle and litle, and bréedeth in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a deadly hatred againſt God, wherby they ronne into foule and heynous facts, and ſo at the laſte fall into tragicall paynes, both in this world and in the world to come. Which the Poets ment alſo to expreſſe in <hi>Iupiter</hi> his conqueſts, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſayd Giauntes called <hi>Philegians,</hi> who were caried quick to Hel, with a floud ſent out by Neptune, of whom Uirgil wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phlegiaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> miſerrimus omnes, Admonet et magna teſtater voce per vmbras, Diſcite inſticia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moniti et no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temnere diuos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How gréeuouſly and odiouſly men doe
<pb facs="tcp:6659:44"/> prophane Gods name by periury, it will <note place="margin">Periury a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uce.</note> playnely appeare by the difinition of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An oath is an aſueration, of a thing poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lawfull, made with the inuocation of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an oth</note> 
                  <hi>Gods name, wherein we pray God to caſte downe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs his malidiction &amp; vengeance, if in ſwearing we ſay vntruth, or wittingly &amp; willingly break our oth,</hi> In bare and naked promiſes; wherein we promiſe to doe true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is ſayd: <hi>Let your communication bee yea, yea, and nay, nay,</hi> but of oathes there are ſeuere preceptes, <hi>Thou ſhalt not forſweare thy ſelfe, but ſhalt performe thine oath to God:</hi> Wherevnto he aodeth a fearefull Communication, <hi>For the lord wil not hold him guiltles that taketh his name in vayne:</hi> There is no doubt but Gods maieſtie and name, is wonderfully abuſed, when men ronne into wilfull periury. For in that we cal vpon him to be our witnes and Iudge. Our wilfull periury denieth him to be a true witnes, argueth him of falſehode, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth his plagues, and bindeth vs by our owne mouthes to abide the ſame. There can then no greater contumely be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt God, nor no more gréeuous crime
<pb facs="tcp:6659:44"/> committed by man then wilfully: to make a mock and by word of Gods name: where vnto if men adde wilful murder, and ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of innocent bloude: they muſt néedes fill vp euen to the brimme, the meaſure of iniquitie.</p>
               <p>Such men are vngraciouſlye ledde and <note place="margin">Of ſynners iudutate &amp; paſt grace.</note> drawne to puniſhment and vengeance: ſo that among ſuch tranſgreſſors, you ſhall ſkarce finde one that hath in this worlde eſcape the reuenging hande of almightie God: as we may plainly ſée by <hi>Caine, Saule, Richarde</hi> king of Englande; the thirde of that name, and infinite other examples. Hereof the Poets haue written thus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ah miſer &amp; ſi quis primum periuria celat, Sera tamen tacitas pena venit pedibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former examples are ſpeciall, but <note place="margin">Examples of Princes and people puniſhed for their periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> when we beholde things more publike, and generall, we ſée a more ſorowfull Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. For we may reade of them eſt noble and flooriſhing Famelies of Princes, to haue beue vtterlye rooted vp, for wicked murders and periurie. And ſo God doth ſhewe himſelfe to be a defender and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of iuſtice and pull it ike order: and that his pleaſure is, that the inteynall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions
<pb facs="tcp:6659:45"/> of mannes mynde, ſhoulde conforme themſelues to the working of Gods ſpirit, and alſo that the external members ſhould be kept within the compaſſe of good lawes and regiment. Which whoſoeuer haue broken, they haue alwayes bene accounted factious, ſeditious, periured, and men no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted otherwiſe, with vile reproches and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fames. Such men were the <hi>Carthaginenſes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Carthage.</note> reputed, who vnconſtant and ſlypping in in all their wordes and promiſes, ſought ſtill by guylefull and craftie interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to illude their othes, who at the laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vtterly ſubdued, and their citie ſticke and ſtone conſumed, euen to the grounde with fyre: doe bidde vs beholde the ende of leuitie and periurie. <hi>Philyp</hi> of <hi>Macedonia</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Philip.</note> was wont to playe with his fayth, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe with ſtickes: which was the cauſe as the wiſe Ethnickes thought of the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne and ſtraunge ruine of all his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for within twelue yeares after his ſon Alexander in the floure of his time, died ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or with immoderate drink whoſe mother, wife, and two ſonnes, were murdered of his Nobles, neither was ther found anye Patrons of ſo royall a famely.
<pb facs="tcp:6659:45"/> And in our fathers dayes <hi>Lewis,</hi> king of <note place="margin">Engenius Pope of Rome and Lewis king of Hungaria.</note> 
                  <hi>Hungaria,</hi> induced by Eugenius biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> brake the league which hee hadde made with Amaruthes the great Turcke: and drew that Tirant to bend all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer agaynſt Chriſtendome, being at that time otherwiſe buſied in the eaſt, in which warre, <hi>Lewis</hi> the king with the greater part of his army, miſerably periſhed, the ſmart whereof not onely <hi>Hungaria</hi> feeteth, but all Chriſtendome lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth at this day. And to omit thoſe thinges that hiſtories re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, many examples as well priuate as publique, daily experience in mans life, do verify the ſame: whereof it came to paſſe that the old writers, appoynted certayne Gods, to be reuengers of periury, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mecide: For they beholding ſuch dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, not without greate admiration, iudged that thoſe thinges came not to paſſe by chaunce, and at adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, but that ſome diuine power was eſpecially appoynted to be the puniſher of Periury &amp; wilful mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And hitherto, I thought in ſome priuate callings and condicions of mans life, to poynt out as it were with the finger, the
<pb facs="tcp:6659:46"/> ioy and ſolace of a pure and ſinerre Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and the endleſſe vexation and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the contrary: now I will diſcend to certein queſtions, which men commonly moue, about mans Conſcience.</p>
               <p>It is demaunded commonly, whether an <note place="margin">Whether is be enough for men to reſt vppon their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> erring Conſcience deeth condemne man: That is to ſay, whether mans will ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and diſcenting from reaſon dceriued, condemneth a man: we muſt obſerue that it is the part of Reaſon, to giue light vnto Will wandring in darrkneſſe, and groſſe ignorannce: and therefore Wil diſcenting from Reaſon diſceiued, muſt néedes offend and doe wickedly. Hée doth euill I ſay, not in his own nature, but becauſe the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſo iudgeth of it ſelf, albeit it be perfite and good.</p>
               <p>And therfore the diuines playnly affirm, that Will diſcenting from Conſcience and Reaſon, whether ſhe be ſincere or corrupt, in what kind of action ſoeuer ſhe be buſied, whether they be good, euell, or indifferent, ſhée offendeth and committeth ſinne.</p>
               <p>And from hence is derided the ſolucion of that queſtion: <hi>Whether the Conſcience erring excuſeth:</hi> That is, whether the Wil
<pb facs="tcp:6659:46"/> conſenting with Reaſon, ſwaruing from truthe offendeth: for if Will diſcenting from Reaſon deceaued tranſgreſſe, ſurely it muſt néedes folow, that the ſame conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with Reaſon doth not offend: <hi>For of thinges contrary, there follow contrary ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quelles,</hi> as not onely <hi>Cicero</hi> but the Logiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans generally, and experience prooueth. We muſt herein obſerue that as a ſéemely and comly body is ſo called, when there is right ſhape and compoſition of all the reſte of the members of mans body: and it is the named euell fauoured if in any one hmme or ioint, there be nay thing vncomly, croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or lawe: euen ſo that is only accounted good, which is abſolute and conſumate in al partes, and ſo it is named euell when any litle thing wanteth, to the perferfection thereof, or to ſpeake playnly and briefely: <hi>Euell proceedeth of ſpecial vices and defects, but goodneſſe of that which is on euery ſide without fault or blemiſhe.</hi> So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is enough if either y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Will be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or Reaſon which is the guide and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Will.</p>
               <p>But this thing wilbe playn by the appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſityon of an example. Thoſe that did both
<pb facs="tcp:6659:47"/> curſe the Apoſtles of Chriſt, &amp; committed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, minding to execute them, with moſt paynfull deathes, thought that they offered a moſt acceptable ſacrifice to God, euen as Chriſt himſelfe beareth witneſſe. The time ſhall come ſayth he, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer killeth you, ſhal thinck he doth GOD good ſeruice.</p>
               <p>Theſe mens reaſons and vnderſtanding was merueylouſly ſhadowed with darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and error, and yet their will and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence did concurre together. And <hi>Paule</hi> himſelfe when he perſecuted the Church of Chriſt, and caſt his ſeruaunts into bondes: had a Will obedient to Reaſon, wandring in great darcknes. And yet that Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward confeſſeth, that albeit, he did that ignorauntly through vnbeliefe: yet that hee gréeuouſly offended God, albeit through re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, he afterward obteyned Gods mercy. For God doth eaſily and ſoone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſimply ignorance repenting the fault, and where mallice and wilfull will wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the faulte is reputed leſſe in Gods ſight.</p>
               <p>I will not haue any man miſtake, me as though I thought that any kinde of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce
<pb facs="tcp:6659:47"/> ſhould eyther excuſe a man, or be accounted tollerable in Gods ſight. For without doubt all kinds of ignoraunce are blame worthy, <hi>Elſe the law in Moyſes ſhold ſeeme to bee in vayne, appoynting a ſacrifice to be offered vnto God for ignorance. Nu. 15. but my meaning is, that ignorantia facti, as they terme it wanting negligence and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, may ſeeme to haue ſome probable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And touching <hi>Paules</hi> error, it had a ſhow of probability and likelihoode. It was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Moyſes</hi> that if any Prophete did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe teaching thinges contrary to the lawe, he ſhould out of hand be ſtoned to death: that Ieſus was ſuch a one, <hi>Paule</hi> herd by the reports almoſt of all men, and that hee was for that cauſe, by the Prieſts, Scribes Phariſies, Seniours, and by conſent of all the people apprehended, accuſed, founde gylty, condemned and finally crucified: for he neuer herd nor ſawe perſonally Chriſt, neyther any of his Apoſtles, teaching or worcking of myracles. <hi>Paules</hi> error there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did ariſe as wel in reſpect of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as of the perſon: Wherein his minde and Reaſon drowned in ignoraunce, hadd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6659:48"/> an agréeable wil, whereby as hee offended, yet that came not to paſſe by wilfull igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, but by a zealous ſtudy of the law, couered with ſimplicity, as him ſelfe to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> witneſſeth.</p>
               <p>The ſcolaſticall diuines doe alſo moue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <note place="margin">The true ground and foundation of a good Conſcience.</note> queſtion, whether the Conſcience bindeth: That is whether a man ought to doe al thinges that his Conſcience mooueth him vnto: Moreouer if it happen Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the ſuperiour maieſtrate to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe things mere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, they aſk which of them a man ought to obey and followe. Wherein this is commonly theire iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Conſcience is alwayes to be moderated and directed by Gods word: wherevnto if it bee agreeable and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, yet it bindeth a man no more then it was before bound by the eternall word of God. And therefore ſuch Conſcience is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be followed and obeyed. But if it doe preſcribe any thing, meere contrary vnto the ſame word, then it is to be correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and amended. For if the leaſt Scruple remaine in the minde, whether a man doe according to the mocion of his Conſcience, or againſt it, bee ſinneth gréeuouſly: For
<pb facs="tcp:6659:48"/> in dooing the one, a man ſinneth agaynſte Gods law, and in dooing the othe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r, thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo offendeſt. For although the deede in it ſelfe be good in Gods ſight, yet man doth it <note place="margin">Doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>angerous.</note> doubtingly, whether it be good or no: which doubt and ſtaggaring of the mind is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue &amp; condemneth a man, <hi>Hereof the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle pronounceth him bleſſed that doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn himſelfe in that he aloweth. Ro. 14.</hi> In which ſentence he telleth vs y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ée may not dee any thing, which leaueth behind it a doubt or remorſe of Conſcience, for hée that doubteth, and yet goeth through wyth the matter, doe moſt playnely centrinne God.</p>
               <p>And moreouer, whiles that hée doth a good thing, doubting with in him ſelfe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or nay: he giueth iuſte occaſion for all men to iudge that hée would alſo not ſtick to doe miſchiefe if eccaſion ſerur. So it commeth to paſſe that the thing which is not euell in it ſelfe, is yet by doubting euel to him ſhat doth it, and his own Conſcience accuſing him, will pronounce ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt him. For this cauſe it is rightly ſaid, that if Reaſon erring and deceiued, doeth preſcribe and appoynt any thing as Gods
<pb facs="tcp:6659:49"/> heſtes, and yet not ſo in déede: that then if the Will doe neglectt Reaſons commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, it is as great an offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as if a man ſhould withſtand the commaundement of God.</p>
               <p>And touching that other queſtion whiche encombreth many men, whether we ought to follow our Conſcience, or the magiſtrate commaunding thinges contrary: in which queſtion if maſter For had at large put down that which hee briefly and finely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and ſhadowed (as it were) in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, before his titles of common places: or if mayſter Mullins would vouchſafe to commit that to writing which hee diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed herein profoundly and learnedly at Paules Croſſe: then I ſhould not want a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that might ſerue to the full diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucion of this queſtion, my opinion is thys. If the Prince or magiſtrate, doe command any thing repuguaunt to Gods Lawe, our Conſciences, witneſſing the ſame: then let vs remember that the Apoſtles and other the faythfull ſeruauntes of Chriſt, in the primatiue church would rather abide pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full impriſonment and ſuſteine moſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull death, then in any one iotte obey
<pb facs="tcp:6659:49"/> their wicked ordinances. The bleſſed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir and Biſhop. <hi>Policarpus</hi> aunſwered the Romayne <hi>Proconſull: Wee are taught to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey princes and Potentates, in thoſe thinges</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Policar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus.</note> 
                  <hi>that be not contrary to ſincere Religion.</hi> And <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſayd diuinely to <hi>Gaynas: It is not lawfull for the Emperour being the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chriſoſt.</note> 
                  <hi>of true Godlines, to attempte any thing againſt the ſame.</hi> The Prince or other ſupreme Magiſtrate, is appoynted the kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of both the tables: but he may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede to decrée any thing withoute the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the Scripture. For <hi>Will worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinges are not acceptable to God,</hi> becauſe they are not agréeable to his eternall wil, neyther can they aſſure mens Conſcience, that they are accepted of God. Wherefore ſuch authority was not geuen to <hi>Moyſes</hi> himſelfe, that he might of himſelfe deuiſe and orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Religion, but God did expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perticulerly by name appoynt theſe thinges which he would haue propoſed to his people to be kept of them. Neyther did be inſtrua <hi>Moyſes</hi> in a moment, but taking <note place="margin">God in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> by degrees.</note> him vp into the mountaine vnto him, by the ſpace of fourty dayes: gaue him inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and afterward leſt any ſimple or
<pb facs="tcp:6659:50"/> doubt ſhould remayne: he ſolemnely autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed his miniſtery by miracles and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the eyes of all the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Neither had the Apoſtles power at their pleaſure, to faſhion and forme what Religion they would, but Chriſt firſte taughte them by mouth, and afterwardes added ſacraments of true Religion, and confirmed the ſame with ſignes and wonders: and finally gaue them commiſſion to teach, and preach thoſe thinges which they had heard, ſeene, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of him.</p>
               <p>And ſo both the Teſtaments haue bene geuen, not by humaine, but by diuine tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and power, confirmed moreouer with many nighty ſignes and wonders: For it is the pleaſure of almighty God, that his miniſters ſhall certeynly knowe his wil, which cannot bée, if men might in any reſped inuent new religions. Which the <note place="margin">Numa Pompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</note> Ethnicks in elder time knew right well, for <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> ſetting by a religion, perſwaded the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> that in the night ſeaſon, <hi>Aegeria</hi> appeared vnto him and reuealed ſuch thinges as he inſtituted. He knewe right well that all opinions of religion are of no valure without the feare
<pb facs="tcp:6659:50"/> of God: and therefore his meaning was that the people ſhould receiue thoſe things as deliuered not by man, but by inſtinction of the powers aboue. And therefore men ſhould excéedingly ſwarue, if for the title of the office of a Magiſtrate, they accept al de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crées and edicts of Religion: which in déede were nothing elſe then of a eccleſiaſtical, to make a ſeculer Pope. Whiles then wée touch that the care of religion apperteineth to Magiſtrates, we meane not that they may at their pleaſures dayly Coyne newe articles of the fayth: but that they ſhoulde follow the examples of Godly Princes, who alwayes in the reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, had an eſpecial eye to the word of god, the lantern and light vnto our pathes, and ſteps.</p>
               <p>Nowe as concerning the princes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall lawes. If they be made to the ende to laye vppon men opinion of religion, as though the obſeruation of them were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie: then the conſcience is burdened and ſnared contrary to godlyneſſe. For in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of conſcience we haue to doe only with God, and not with man. In ſome places the ſcripture ſéemeth to extende the ſame to
<pb facs="tcp:6659:51"/> men, as when Paule ſayth, he walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man with a pure conſcience, but that is bicauſe the fruites of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth iſſue and flowe amongſt good men: but properly as I ſayde it appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to God onely, neyther doth that place of ſaint Paule to the Romaines proue, that contrarie where a diſtinction ought to be obſerued. For although euerye perticuler lawe reach not to the conſcience, by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall precept, yet obedience to the magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate is comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, bicauſe they be of God: but the cyuill lawes of princes, eyther tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching common profite, pleaſure, vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and comelyneſſe, being eyther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or pleaſant are to obſerued &amp; kept. For althoughe in their properties they be indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: yet by meanes of authority they are almoſt equyualent with Gods lawes: and are not by anye meanes to be violated and broken, onleſſe extreme neceſſitie vrge and as it were inferre violently to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame. Neceſſitie in déede is pardoned, if wilfull arrogancie and malicious contempt of our ſuperiours be abſent. For in ſuch caſes, God reſpecteth the minde and not the fact: and where no wilfulneſſe is, there is hys
<pb facs="tcp:6659:51"/> mercie moſt readie. And for as much as the lawe of God ſometime giueth place to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie: as when Dauid againſt the lawe did eate of the Shewbread, whome Chriſt defendeth: why ſhould not mannes ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nannces a great deale more doe the ſame, ſo that Malaparteneſſe and contumacy of our ſuperioures, and the offence of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren be farre from vs.</p>
               <p>It now reſteth only, that neither thoſe <note place="margin">Two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tyons the firſt agaynſt bayn confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in one own rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſeneſſe.</note> that haue good Conſcience doe truſt in their own merites, neither yet hauing an euel Conſcience for his fylthy and abhominable life, ſhould fall inio diſpaire: and ſo finally ronne into deſperation. That of ſaynt <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> is diuiuely ſpoken. <hi>Conſcience and Fame are two things, Conſcience is needeful to thy ſelfe, and Fame for thy neighbour: But if thou reſpect thy good name to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, &amp; yet it nothing auaileth thee, be thou quiet in thy ſelfe, becauſe of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the ſight of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet no man ought arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to haue affiaunce in his good worckes, and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaically to pleaſe himſelf, and to contemne others: For the modeſty of ſinners diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them ſelues for their offences, is much
<pb facs="tcp:6659:52"/> acceptable in Gods ſight, then the worckes and merites of thoſe who in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite accoumpt themſelues iuſt. Whiche thing is clearely ſéene in the parable of the Phariſie and Publican, whereof the one puſt vp with the opinion of his owne good worcks (which affection encombreth euen good men ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnleſſe they dilligently take héede) diſpleaſeth God, pleaſing himſelfe ouer much: not only a flatterer of himſelf, but contumelious to his neighboure. The other male content with himſelfe, for hys guilts and offences, and beating his breſte with moſt humble voyce, craued gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: and ſo the more he was diſpleaſed with himſelfe, the more he pleaſed God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of Saynt <hi>Auguſt. The iuſtice as it were of God, looked downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſaying: let vs ſpare this man, becauſe hee ſpared not himſelfe, let vs forgiue him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee forgaue not himſelfe, he conuerted himſelf to puniſh his ſinne, let vs conuerte to deliuer him. Auguſt. pſa. 48.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſelfe loue and good opinion of oure ſelues ought to be eſchewed, and it is beſte for vs to thinck ſimply of our ſelues, and to ſay with <hi>Danyell.</hi> Wée haue offended, we
<pb facs="tcp:6659:52"/> haue committed iniquity, we haue declined and gone aſtray from the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. To thée O Lord belongeth glory, and Iuſtice, but to vs ſhame &amp; confuſion. For he glorifieth God that accounteth him ſelfe a ſinner, and repenting, putteth hys whole truſt and confydence in Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: whereas proude Phariſes iudge eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to be the reward of their vertues, and good worcks.</p>
               <p>And what is ſinfull man able to doe of himſelfe: or if he be hable to doe any thing is not that to be attributed to Gods grace, by whoſe gift we are that we are: ſo that in all thinges, vnleſſe we will be ouer impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, we muſt néedes graunt our excéeding great imbecility, and Gods infinite mercy. That truſt therefore in our own merites, and vayne opinion of our righteouſeneſſe, which will not ſuffer a man to bee humble and lowly: but ſtirreth him to pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy, is by al meanes as a peſtelence to be eſchewed.</p>
               <p>For God highly diſpleaſed there with, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth from man the right hande of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and ſuffereth vs to haue the raynes at our will and pleaſure: wherewith wée
<pb facs="tcp:6659:53"/> runne into ruine and deſtruction. And that I may leaue externall accions, when wee hapely may be blamles in the eyes of man; who dare once open his mouth to ſaye my heart is cleane, ſéeing that <hi>Iob</hi> in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion crieth ſaying, <hi>Can that be cleane which is borne of a woman, not one, albeit hee liue but a day vpon the face of the earth?</hi> And S. <hi>Iohn, if we ſay we haue no ſinne we deceaue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs. But if we confeſſe our ſinnes, he is ſaythful and iuſt to forgiue vs the ſame, and the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt doth purge vs cleane from al iniquity.</hi> This ſentence of that excelent Apoſtle and ſo welbeloued of God, taketh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hipocrits al vayne truſt and confidence in their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites: and miniſtreth great conſolation and vnſpekeable comfort, to afflicted conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, and ſuch as bée vnquieted for their crimes, and offences, wherewithall they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraunged the countenance of their louing father from them.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>This is our boaſting euen the teſtimony of our conſcience.</hi> But he ſayeth again: <hi>He that reioceth let him reioice in the lord, euery man may reioice then in his good deedes, but not without the Lord.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:6659:53"/> we muſt alwayes remember theſe three Cawtelles, firſt that we acknowledge all our goodneſſe to come from God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that we put our truſt and confidc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in God alone: Thirdly, that we reſte and repoſe our ſelues wholy in God the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and author of all goodneſſe. Theſe foundations being layd: then I ſay it is not only good but alſo néedeful, that we reioyce in our good déedes, not with vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> or the glorious hipocrite, but in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and comfort of our good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>Neyther may the wounded Conſcience, <note place="margin">Agaynſt ſorrow and diſpayre of an aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eted Conſcience</note> (which is as it were a taſte of eternal deth) diſpaire of ſaluation, becauſe of their hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſinnes and offences: for they haue the merites and death of chriſt for their refuge and ſanctuary. For oure heauenly father moſt tenderly and dearely louing vs, hath giuen his onely ſonne to the death of the Croſſe for vs, to obtein ſaluation, he hath giuen him vnto vs by whome he is pleaſed and reconciled to man, the remembraunce of our ſins ſtriken out, ſo that we certeinly perſwade our ſelf therof, and hauing this fayth doe wholy yeld our ſelues vnto him.
<pb facs="tcp:6659:54"/> Hereof ſpeaketh y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Apoſtle, if any man ſin, we haue an adudcaſe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, &amp; he is the propitiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes, not for our ſins only, but for the ſins of the whole world, and that ſaying is very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable: <hi>What time ſoeuer a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth repent him of his ſinne, I will put all his wickedneſſe out of my remembrance.</hi> And again. <hi>As truely as I liue ſayth the lord, I would not the death of a ſinner, but that he ſhould conuert and liue.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like ſentences doe comfort vs againſt deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into the which <hi>Caine, Saule</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> by diffidence fel, and with an oth God doth aſſure vs of his loue &amp; mercy, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer diſpaireth of, he accuſeth god of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, being moſt heynous impiety, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth Chriſtes ſacrifyce to be auaileable to put away our ſinnes. For our louing God doth principally requeſt this at our hands, that we diſtruſting our ſelues, ſhould truſt and commit our ſelues only to him, whoſe loue and charity toward vs, hath appeared aboundantly, that he hath geuen his only ſonne for wicked and ſinfull men for hys enemies, whereby he might receiue vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, into his loue &amp; gracious ſauoure, with
<pb facs="tcp:6659:54"/> this fayth and confidence a ſinful man may ſtay himſelf, and aſſure vnto him moſte firme conſolations and defence, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wraſtleth with the pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs and agonyes of ſinne, death, and deſperation: where vnto often times a man is drawen, and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as it were of an hangman, by his own vnquiet Conſcience, or by the malicious and guileful temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of his mortal and capitall enemy the Deuill.</p>
               <p>And theſe thinges I thought good to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to writing, touching the good and euell <note place="margin">The coucin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Conſcience, wherein we ſee that as there is nothing more horrible and peruicidus then the euel Conſcience, doubting, miſtruſting and deſpairing in all things: ſo there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better, nor more comfortable then a good Conſcience, which maketh a man liue euen a bleſſed life vpon earth, and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto him ſincere and perfite pleaſure. Seing then the commodity of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is ſo great, and that no man can haue it, vnleſſe he liue in his vocation, and doe his duety vprightly. It ſtandeth euery man vpon to endeuour and bende all his power and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth euen vnto the vttermoſt, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtie and aunſwere the ſame, which that I
<pb facs="tcp:6659:55"/> may ſpeake bréefely, is to abandon vice and embrace vertue, ſo ſhal we be partakers of ſuch an ineſtimable ioy and treaſure. So ſhall no good man deuiſe or practiſe any fraude or guyle: he ſhall not offer any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury to his neighbour, and ſo to conclude ſhal vice be baniſhed, and vertues, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, piety, Iuſtice, peace, concord, and ſuch other like, ſhal ſpring and floriſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. God the author and giuer of all good giftes graunt vs al this excellent treaſure, that in all our actions we may weigh and conſider our Conſcience, being a dayly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omeſtical Iudge, wherby we ſhalbe ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from committing thoſe thinges whiche offend his high maieſtie: that ſo liuing holyly and ſincerely in this world, we may in the other world, come to perfite bliſſe and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6659:55"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
